{"antonyms":[{"question":"ENORMOUS","options":{"A":"Soft","B":"Average","C":"Tiny","D":"Weak"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Tiny"},{"question":"COMMISSIONED","options":{"A":"Started","B":"Closed","C":"Finished","D":"Terminated"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Terminated"},{"question":"ARTIFICIAL","options":{"A":"Red","B":"Natural","C":"Truthful","D":"Solid"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Natural"},{"question":"EXODUS","options":{"A":"Influx","B":"Home-coming","C":"Return","D":"Restoration"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Influx"},{"question":"RELINQUISH","options":{"A":"Abdicate","B":"Renounce","C":"Possess","D":"Deny"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Possess"},{"question":"EXPAND","options":{"A":"Convert","B":"Condense","C":"Congest","D":"Conclude"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Condense"},{"question":"MORTAL","options":{"A":"Divine","B":"Immortal","C":"Spiritual","D":"Eternal"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Immortal"},{"question":"QUIESCENT","options":{"A":"ACTIVE","B":"Dormant","C":"Weak","D":"Unconcerned"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"ACTIVE"},{"question":"History abounds in instances of courage.","options":{"A":"shines","B":"lacks","C":"suffices","D":"fails"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"lacks"},{"question":"The inhabitants of the island were barbarians.","options":{"A":"civilized","B":"cruel","C":"uncivilized","D":"bad"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"civilized"},{"question":"The members thought that the task was feasible.","options":{"A":"impractical","B":"impossible","C":"difficult","D":"impracticable"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"impractical"},{"question":"crestfallen he returned as he had never faced such humiliation in the whole of his life.","options":{"A":"vainglorious","B":"indignant","C":"triumphant","D":"disturbed"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"triumphant"},{"question":"Feasibility of the project is under study.","options":{"A":"unsuitability","B":"cheapness","C":"impropriety","D":"impracticability"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"impracticability"}],"change-of-speech":[{"question":"\"If you don't keep quiet I shall shoot you\", he said to her in a calm voice.","options":{"A":"Hewarnedhertoshootifshedidn'tkeepquietcalmly.","B":"HesaidcalmlythatIshallshootyouifyoudon'tbequiet.","C":"Hewarnedhercalmlythathewouldshootherifshedidn'tkeepquiet.","D":"Calmlyhewarnedherthatbequietorelsehewillhavetoshoother."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Hewarnedhercalmlythathewouldshootherifshedidn'tkeepquiet."},{"question":"I told him that he was not working hard.","options":{"A":"Isaidtohim,\"Youarenotworkinghard.\"","B":"Itoldtohim,\"Youarenotworkinghard.\"","C":"Isaid,\"Youarenotworkinghard.\"","D":"Isaidtohim,\"Heisnotworkinghard.\""},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Isaidtohim,\"Youarenotworkinghard.\""},{"question":"His father ordered him to go to his room and study.","options":{"A":"Hisfathersaid,\"Gotoyourroomandstudy.\"","B":"Hisfathersaidtohim,\"Goandstudyinyourroom.\"","C":"Hisfathershouted,\"Gorightnowtoyourstudyroom\"","D":"Hisfathersaidfirmly,\"Goandstudyinyourroom.\""},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Hisfathersaid,\"Gotoyourroomandstudy.\""},{"question":"He said to his father, \"Please increase my pocket-money.\"","options":{"A":"Hetoldhisfather,\"Pleaseincreasethepocket-money\"","B":"Hepleadedhisfathertopleaseincreasemypocketmoney.","C":"Herequestedhisfathertoincreasehispocket-money.","D":"Heaskedhisfathertoincreasehispocket-money."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Herequestedhisfathertoincreasehispocket-money."},{"question":"She said that her brother was getting married.","options":{"A":"Shesaid,\"Herbrotherisgettingmarried.\"","B":"Shetold,\"Herbrotherisgettingmarried.\"","C":"Shesaid,\"Mybrotherisgettingmarried.\"","D":"Shesaid,\"Mybrotherwasgettingmarried.\""},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Shesaid,\"Mybrotherisgettingmarried.\""}],"change-of-voice":[{"question":"After driving professor Kumar to the museum she dropped him at his hotel.","options":{"A":"Afterbeingdriventothemuseum,ProfessorKumarwasdroppedathishotel.","B":"ProfessorKumarwasbeingdrivendroppedathishotel.","C":"AftershehaddrivenProfessorKumartothemuseumshehaddroppedhimathishotel.","D":"AftershewasdrivenProfessorKumartothemuseumshehaddroppedhimathishotel."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Afterbeingdriventothemuseum,ProfessorKumarwasdroppedathishotel."},{"question":"I remember my sister taking me to the museum.","options":{"A":"IrememberIwastakentothemuseumbymysister.","B":"Irememberbeingtakentothemuseumbymysister.","C":"Iremembermyselfbeingtakentothemuseumbymysister.","D":"Iremembertakentothemuseumbymysister."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Irememberbeingtakentothemuseumbymysister."},{"question":"Who is creating this mess?","options":{"A":"Whohasbeencreatedthismess?","B":"Bywhomhasthismessbeencreated?","C":"Bywhomthismessisbeingcreated?","D":"Bywhomisthismessbeingcreated?"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Bywhomisthismessbeingcreated?"},{"question":"They greet me cheerfully every morning.","options":{"A":"EverymorningIwasgreetedcheerfully.","B":"Iamgreetedcheerfullybythemeverymorning.","C":"Iambeinggreetedcheerfullybythemeverymorning.","D":"Cheerfulgreetingisdonebythemeverymorningtome."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Iamgreetedcheerfullybythemeverymorning."},{"question":"Darjeeling grows tea.","options":{"A":"TeaisbeinggrowninDarjeeling.","B":"LettheteabegrowninDarjeeling.","C":"TeaisgrowninDarjeeling.","D":"TeagrowsinDarjeeling."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"TeaisgrowninDarjeeling."}],"completing-statements":[{"question":"Despite his best efforts to conceal his anger ......","options":{"A":"wecoulddetectthathewasveryhappy","B":"hefailedtogiveusanimpressionofhisagony","C":"hesucceededincamouflaginghisemotions","D":"hecouldsucceedindoingiteasily","E":"peoplecametoknowthathewasannoyed"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"peoplecametoknowthathewasannoyed"},{"question":"Even if it rains I shall come means ......","options":{"A":"ifIcomeitwillnotrain","B":"ifitrainsIshallnotcome","C":"Iwillcertainlycomewhetheritrainsornot","D":"wheneverthereisrainIshallcome","E":"Iamlesslikelytocomeifitrains"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Iwillcertainlycomewhetheritrainsornot"},{"question":"His appearance is unsmiling but ......","options":{"A":"hisheartisfullofcompassionforothers","B":"helooksveryseriousonmostoccasions","C":"peopleareafraidofhim","D":"heisuncompromisingonmattersoftaskperformance","E":"heisfullofjealousytowardshiscolleagues"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"hisheartisfullofcompassionforothers"},{"question":"She never visits any zoo because she is strong opponent of the idea of ......","options":{"A":"settingtheanimalsfreeintoforest","B":"feedingtheanimalswhileothersarewatching","C":"watchingtheanimalsintheirnaturalabode","D":"goingoutofthehouseonaholiday","E":"holdingtheanimalsincaptivityforourjoy"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"holdingtheanimalsincaptivityforourjoy"},{"question":"I felt somewhat more relaxed ......","options":{"A":"buttenseascomparedtoearlier","B":"andtenseascomparedtoearlier","C":"astherewasalreadynotensionatall","D":"andtension-freeascomparedtoearlier","E":"becausetheworryhadalreadycapturedbymind"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"andtension-freeascomparedtoearlier"},{"question":"It is not easy to remain tranquil when those around you ......","options":{"A":"behaveinasociallyacceptablemanner","B":"exhibitpleasantmannerism","C":"arelosingtheirheads","D":"agreetowhateveryousay","E":"exhibitgenerousandmagnanimousgestures"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"arelosingtheirheads"},{"question":"\"The food in this hotel is no match to what were forced at late hours in Hotel Kohinoor \" means ......","options":{"A":"Thefoodinthishotelisquitegoodcomparedtowhatweateatkohinoor","B":"Hotelkohinoorservedusgoodqualityfoodthanwhatwegethere","C":"Bothhotelshavemaintainedgoodqualityoffood","D":"Bothhotelsservepoorqualityoffood","E":"itisbettertoeatfoodthanremainhungry"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Hotelkohinoorservedusgoodqualityfoodthanwhatwegethere"},{"question":"Although initial investigations pointed towards him ......","options":{"A":"theprecedingeventscorroboratedhisinvolvementinthecrime","B":"theadditionalinformationconfirmedhisguilt","C":"thesubsequenteventsestablishedthathewasguilt","D":"thesubsequenteventsprovedthathewasinnocent","E":"hegaveanopenconfessionofhiscrime"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"thesubsequenteventsprovedthathewasinnocent"},{"question":"The weather outside was extremely pleasant and hence we decided to ......","options":{"A":"utiliseourtimeinwatchingthetelevision","B":"refrainfromgoingoutforamorningwalk","C":"enjoyamorningrideintheopen","D":"employthisrareopportunityforwritingletters","E":"remainseatedinourroomsinthebungalow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"enjoyamorningrideintheopen"},{"question":"\"It is an uphill task but you will have to do it\" means ......","options":{"A":"Theworkisabovethehillandyouwillhavetodoit","B":"Itisaveryeasytaskbutyoumustdoit","C":"Itisverydifficulttaskbutyouhavetodoit","D":"Thisworkisnotreservedforyoubutyouwillhavetodoit","E":"Itisalmostimpossibleforothersbutyoucandoit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Itisverydifficulttaskbutyouhavetodoit"},{"question":"\" You are thinking very highly about Ravi but he is not so\" means ......","options":{"A":"Raviisasgoodasyouthinkabouthim","B":"YouhaveagoodopinionaboutRavibutheisnotasgoodasyouthink","C":"YourviewaboutRaviisphilosophical,keepitup","D":"Raviismuchbetter,thanwhatyouthinkofhim","E":"YouhaveagoodopinionaboutRavibuthedoesnothaveagoodopinionaboutyou"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"YouhaveagoodopinionaboutRavibutheisnotasgoodasyouthink"},{"question":"\"Anand stuck up a friendship with Mahesh in just 2 days\" means ......","options":{"A":"AnandfriendshipwithMaheshcametoanendrecently","B":"AnandfoundouttheotherfriendsofMahesh","C":"AnandfixedadealwithMaheshin2days","D":"Anand'sfriendshipwithMaheshlastedfor2years","E":"AnandbecameafriendofMaheshinlessthan2days"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"AnandbecameafriendofMaheshinlessthan2days"},{"question":"Although, he is reputed for making very candid statements ......","options":{"A":"histodayspeechwasnotfairlyaudible","B":"hispromiseshadalwaysbeenrealistic","C":"hisspeechwasveryinteresting","D":"peoplefollowwhateverheinstructstothem","E":"histoday'sstatementswereveryambiguous"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"histoday'sstatementswereveryambiguous"},{"question":"The manager would like you to help Dhiraj, means ......","options":{"A":"themanagerwouldlikeyouifyouhelpDhiraj","B":"themanagerdesiresyoutohelpDhiraj","C":"themanagerlikesyoubecauseyouhelpDhiraj","D":"Dhirajexpectsthemanagertotellyoutohelphim","E":"itwillbeahelptothemanagerifyoulikeDhiraj"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"themanagerdesiresyoutohelpDhiraj"},{"question":"Owing to the acute power shortage, the people of our locality have decided to ......","options":{"A":"dispensewithothernon-conventionalenergysources","B":"resorttoabundantuseofelectricityforillumination","C":"off-switchtheelectricalappliancewhilenotinuse","D":"exploreotheravenuesforutilisingtheexcesspower","E":"resorttouseofelectricityonlywhenitisinevitable"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"resorttouseofelectricityonlywhenitisinevitable"},{"question":"He has no money now ......","options":{"A":"althoughhewasverypooronce","B":"ashehasgivenupallhiswealth","C":"becausehewasveryrichonce","D":"becausehehasreceivedhugedonation","E":"becausehewasverygreedyaboutwealth"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"ashehasgivenupallhiswealth"},{"question":"He is so lazy that he ......","options":{"A":"cannotdependonothersforgettinghisworkdone","B":"cannotdelaythescheduleofcompletingthework","C":"canseldomcompletehisworkontime","D":"disliketopostponetheworkthatheundertakestodo","E":"alwayshelpotherstocompletetheirwork"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"canseldomcompletehisworkontime"},{"question":"Dinesh is as stupid as he is lazy means ......","options":{"A":"Dineshisstupidbecauseheislazy","B":"Dineshislazybecauseheisstupid","C":"Dineshiseitherstupidorlazy","D":"Dineshishardlystupidbutheislazy","E":"Dineshisequallystupidandlazy"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Dineshisequallystupidandlazy"},{"question":"Practically, very little work could be completed in the last week as it was ......","options":{"A":"fullofworkingdays","B":"averyhecticweek","C":"fullofholidays","D":"averybusyweek","E":"loadedwithwork"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"fullofholidays"},{"question":"Because he believes in democratic principles, he always ......","options":{"A":"decidesallthemattershimself","B":"listentoothersviewsandenforceshisown","C":"shownrespecttoothersopinionsiftheymatchhisown","D":"reconcileswiththemajorityviewsandgivesushisown","E":"imposeshisownviewsonothers"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"reconcileswiththemajorityviewsandgivesushisown"},{"question":"With great efforts his son succeeded in convincing him not to donate his entire wealth to an orphanage ......","options":{"A":"andleadthelifeofawealthymerchant","B":"buttoahomefortheforsakenchildren","C":"andmakeanorphanofhimself","D":"astheorphanageneededalotofdonations","E":"astheorphanagehadbeensetupbyhim"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"andmakeanorphanofhimself"},{"question":"The employer appeared to be in such an affable mood that Rohit ......","options":{"A":"decidedtoaskforaraiseinhissalary","B":"wasscaredtotalktohimabouthisleave","C":"feltveryguiltyforhisinadvertentslip","D":"promisedhimthathewouldnotcommitmistakeagain","E":"waspainedtopresshisdemandforanewflat."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"decidedtoaskforaraiseinhissalary"},{"question":"He always stammers in public meetings, but his today's speech ......","options":{"A":"wasfairlyaudibletoeveryonepresentinthehall","B":"wasnotreceivedsatisfactorily","C":"couldnotbeunderstoodproperly","D":"wasnotlikedbytheaudience","E":"wasfreefromthatdefect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"wasfreefromthatdefect"},{"question":"Even though it is very large house, ......","options":{"A":"thereisalotofspaceavailableinitforchildren","B":"thereishardlyanyspaceavailableforchildren","C":"thereisnodearthofspaceforchildren","D":"theservantstakealongtimetocleanit","E":"themunicipaltaxesonitareveryhappy"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"thereishardlyanyspaceavailableforchildren"},{"question":"It was an extremely pleasant surprise for the hutment-dweller when the Government officials told him that ......","options":{"A":"hehadtovacatehutmentwhichhehadbeenunauthorisedlyoccupying","B":"hehadbeengiftedwithafurnishedapartmentinamulti-storeyedbuilding","C":"hewouldbearrestedforwrongfullyencroachingonthepavementoutsidehisdwelling","D":"theywouldnotaccedetohisrequest","E":"theyhadreceivedtheordersfromthecourttotakepossessionofallhisbelongings"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hehadbeengiftedwithafurnishedapartmentinamulti-storeyedbuilding"},{"question":"In order to help the company attain its goal of enhancing profit, all the employees ......","options":{"A":"urgedthemanagementtograntpaidleave","B":"appealedthemanagementtoimplementnewwelfareschemes","C":"voluntarilyofferedtoworkovertimewithlucrativecompensation","D":"voluntarilyofferedtorenderadditionalservicesinlieuofnothing","E":"decidedtoenhanceproductionatthecostofqualityoftheproduct"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"voluntarilyofferedtorenderadditionalservicesinlieuofnothing"},{"question":"\"Whatever Dev uttered was without rhyme or reason\" means ......","options":{"A":"Devcouldnotreciteanypoemorspeech","B":"Devsaidsomethingwhichhasnomeaning,itwastotallybaseless","C":"Devwastalkingsomethingwhichwasbeyondourexperience","D":"Devspokeflatlywithoutanyemotionorreason","E":"Devdidnotrefertoanypoemtosupporthisstatements"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Devsaidsomethingwhichhasnomeaning,itwastotallybaseless"},{"question":"He tames animals because he ......","options":{"A":"isfondofthem","B":"hatesthem","C":"isafraidofthem","D":"wanttosetthemfree","E":"seldomlovesthem"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"isfondofthem"},{"question":"Mahesh need not have purchased the bag, means ......","options":{"A":"itwasnotnecessaryforMaheshtopurchasethebagbuthehaspurchasedit","B":"itwasnecessaryforMaheshtopurchasethebagandhehasnotpurchasedit","C":"itwasnotnecessaryforMaheshtopurchasethebagandhehasnotpurchasedit","D":"itwasnecessaryforMaheshtopurchasethebagbuthehasnotpurchasedit","E":"Maheshalreadyhasabagbutstillhepurchasedanotherone"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"itwasnotnecessaryforMaheshtopurchasethebagbuthehaspurchasedit"},{"question":"In order to raise company's profit, the employees ......","options":{"A":"demandedtwoadditionalincrements","B":"decidedtogoonpaidholidays","C":"requestedthemanagementtoimplementnewwelfareschemes","D":"offeredtoworkovertimewithoutanycompensation","E":"decidedtoraisethecostofrawmaterial"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"offeredtoworkovertimewithoutanycompensation"},{"question":"The officer who had neglected to files his income tax returns had to ......","options":{"A":"returnthefiles","B":"payafine","C":"berewarded","D":"playmischief","E":"givewarning"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"payafine"},{"question":"Unless you work harder you will fail, means ......","options":{"A":"ifyoufailyouwillworkharder","B":"youmustatleastplanwellthanyouwillnotfail","C":"hardlyyouwillfailifyoudonotdesireso","D":"ifyoudonotputmoreefforts,thenyouwillfail","E":"ifyouonlyworkandworkalone,youwillfail"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ifyoudonotputmoreefforts,thenyouwillfail"},{"question":"His behaviour is so unpredictable that he ......","options":{"A":"neverdependsuponothersforgettinghisworkdone","B":"isseldomtrustedbyothers","C":"alwaysfindsitdifficulttokeephisword","D":"alwaysinsistsongettingtheworkcompletedontime","E":"seldomtrustsothersasfarastheworkscheduleisconcerned"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"isseldomtrustedbyothers"}],"comprehension":[{"question":"The word 'Command Module' used twice in the given passage indicates perhaps that it deals with","options":{"A":"analarmingjourney","B":"acommandingsituation","C":"ajourneyintoouterspace","D":"afrightfulbattle."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"ajourneyintoouterspace"},{"question":"Which one of the following reasons would one consider as more as possible for the warning lights to be on?","options":{"A":"Therewasashowerofdebris.","B":"Jackwasyelling.","C":"Acatastrophewasimminent.","D":"Themoonwasloomingcloseandbig."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Acatastrophewasimminent."},{"question":"The statement that the dazzling sunshine was \"for once unfiltered by layers of air\" means","options":{"A":"thatthesunwasveryhot","B":"thattherewasnostrongwind","C":"thattheairwasunpolluted","D":"noneofabove"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"noneofabove"},{"question":"The phrase 'Preoccupied grandmotherly air' signifies","options":{"A":"beingtotallyunconcerned","B":"pretendingtobeverybusy","C":"averysuperiorattitude","D":"calm,dignifiedandaffectionatedisposition"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"calm,dignifiedandaffectionatedisposition"},{"question":"From the passage it appears that the author was","options":{"A":"aninexperiencedhunter","B":"kindandconsiderate","C":"possessedwithfear","D":"aworriedman"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"kindandconsiderate"},{"question":"The author did not want to shoot the elephant because he","options":{"A":"wasafraidofit","B":"didnothavetheexperienceofshootingbiganimals","C":"didnotwishtokillanimalwhichwasnotdoinganybodyanyharm","D":"didnotfindtheelephanttobeferocious"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"didnothavetheexperienceofshootingbiganimals"},{"question":"In his dream Harold found the loathsome creatures","options":{"A":"inhisvillage","B":"inhisownhouse","C":"inadifferentland","D":"inhisoffice"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"inadifferentland"},{"question":"Which one of the following phrases best helps to bring out the precise meaning of 'loathsome creatures'?","options":{"A":"Securitybugandslimytentacles","B":"Fearfuldreamandslug-likeanimals","C":"Slimytentaclesandslug-likeanimals","D":"slug-likeanimalsandsecuritybug"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Slimytentaclesandslug-likeanimals"},{"question":"The statement that 'he later threw off the security bug' means that","options":{"A":"Haroldsucceededinovercomingtheneedforsecurity","B":"Haroldstoppedgivingmuchimportancetodreams","C":"Haroldstartedtoleratingsocialvictimisation","D":"Haroldkilledallthebugstroubledhim"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Haroldsucceededinovercomingtheneedforsecurity"},{"question":"Harold's dream was fearful because","options":{"A":"itbroughthimfacetofacewithreality","B":"itwasfullofvividpicturesofsnakes","C":"hesawhugeelephantinit","D":"inithesawslimycreaturesfeedingonpeople'sbodies"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"itbroughthimfacetofacewithreality"},{"question":"If a piece of matter violates nature's law, it is not punished because","options":{"A":"itisnotbindingtoobeyit","B":"thereisnosuperiorbeingtoenforcethelawofnature","C":"itcannotbepunished","D":"itsimplymeansthatthefactshavenotbeencorrectlystatedbylaw"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"thereisnosuperiorbeingtoenforcethelawofnature"},{"question":"Laws of nature differ from man-made laws because","options":{"A":"theformerstatefactsofNature","B":"theymustbeobeyed","C":"theyarenatural","D":"unlikehumanlaws,theyaresystematic"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"theformerstatefactsofNature"},{"question":"The laws of nature based on observation are","options":{"A":"conclusionaboutthenatureoftheuniverse.","B":"trueandunfalsifiable.","C":"figmentsoftheobserverimagination.","D":"subjecttochangeinthelightofnewfacts."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"subjecttochangeinthelightofnewfacts."},{"question":"The author is not happy with word 'law' because","options":{"A":"itconnotesrigidityandharshness","B":"itimpliesanagencywhichhasmadethem","C":"itdoesnotconveythesenseofnature'suniformity","D":"itgivesrisetofalsebeliefs"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"itconnotesrigidityandharshness"},{"question":"According to the passage male lions generally do not go for huntings because","options":{"A":"theydonnotlikeit.","B":"theywantlionesstogettraining","C":"theywishtosavetheirvigourforotherthings","D":"theyareverylazy"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"theywishtosavetheirvigourforotherthings"},{"question":"Male lions protect their cubs","options":{"A":"fromthemembersoftheirownspecies","B":"fromhyenasonly","C":"fromhyenasasmuchasfromotherenemies","D":"morefromhyenasthanfromotheranimals"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"morefromhyenasthanfromotheranimals"},{"question":"Lioness go for hunting","options":{"A":"allalone","B":"withtheirmalepartnersonly","C":"withtheircubsandmalepartners","D":"withtheircubsonly"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"withtheircubsandmalepartners"},{"question":"When the lionesses go in search for their prey, they are very","options":{"A":"serious","B":"cautious","C":"playful","D":"sluggish"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"cautious"},{"question":"According to the author of 'Mentality' of a nation is mainly product of its","options":{"A":"history","B":"internationalposition","C":"politics","D":"presentcharacter"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"history"},{"question":"The need for a greater understanding between nations","options":{"A":"wasalwaysthere","B":"isnolongerthere","C":"ismoretodaythaneverbefore","D":"willalwaysbethere"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"ismoretodaythaneverbefore"},{"question":"The character of a nation is the result of its","options":{"A":"mentality","B":"culturalheritage","C":"grossignorance","D":"socio-politicalconditions"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"socio-politicalconditions"},{"question":"According to the author his countrymen should","options":{"A":"readthestoryofothernations","B":"haveabetterunderstandingofothernations","C":"notreacttootheractions","D":"havevitalcontactswithothernations"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"haveabetterunderstandingofothernations"},{"question":"Englishmen like others to react to political situations like","options":{"A":"us","B":"themselves","C":"others","D":"eachothers"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"themselves"},{"question":"The employees in our country","options":{"A":"arequitepunctualbutnotdutyconscious","B":"arenotpunctual,butsomehowmanagetocompletetheirwork","C":"aresomewhatlazybutgoodnatured","D":"arenotveryhighlyqualified"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"arequitepunctualbutnotdutyconscious"},{"question":"According to the writer, the administration in India","options":{"A":"isbyandlargeeffective","B":"isverystrictandfirm","C":"isaffectedbyredtape","D":"ismoreorlessineffective"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ismoreorlessineffective"},{"question":"The word 'assessment' means","options":{"A":"enquiry","B":"report","C":"evaluation","D":"summary"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"evaluation"},{"question":"The leadership in administration","options":{"A":"setsafineexampletotheemployees","B":"isofareasonablyhighstandard","C":"iscomposedofidealists","D":"isofaverypoorstandard"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"isofaverypoorstandard"},{"question":"The central idea of passage could be best expressed by the following","options":{"A":"Theemployeeoutlooktowardsworkisjustified","B":"Theemployeemustchangetheiroutlooktowardswork","C":"Theemployeeswouldneverchangetheirworkculture","D":"Theemployer-employeerelationshipisfarfromhealthy"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Theemployeemustchangetheiroutlooktowardswork"},{"question":"The best way to win a friend is to avoid","options":{"A":"ironyinspeech","B":"pomposityinspeech","C":"verbosityinspeech","D":"ambiguityinspeech"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ambiguityinspeech"},{"question":"While talking to an uneducated person, we should use","options":{"A":"ordinaryspeech","B":"hisvocabulary","C":"simplewords","D":"politelanguage"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hisvocabulary"},{"question":"If one used the same style of language with everyone, one would sound","options":{"A":"flat","B":"boring","C":"foolish","D":"democratic"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"foolish"},{"question":"A 'slip of the tongue' means something said","options":{"A":"wronglybychoice","B":"unintentionally","C":"withoutgivingproperthought","D":"tohurtanotherperson"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"withoutgivingproperthought"},{"question":"Speech can be curse, because it can","options":{"A":"hurtothers","B":"leadtocarelessness","C":"createmisunderstanding","D":"revealourintentions"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"createmisunderstanding"}],"idioms-and-phrases":[{"question":"To make clean breast of","options":{"A":"Togainprominence","B":"Topraiseoneself","C":"Toconfesswithoutofreserve","D":"Todestroybeforeitblooms","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Toconfesswithoutofreserve"},{"question":"To keeps one's temper","options":{"A":"Tobecomehungry","B":"Tobeingoodmood","C":"Topreserveonesenergy","D":"Tobealooffrom","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Tobeingoodmood"},{"question":"To catch a tartar","options":{"A":"Totrapwantedcriminalwithgreatdifficulty","B":"Tocatchadangerousperson","C":"Tomeetwithdisaster","D":"Todealwithapersonwhoismorethanone'smatch","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Tocatchadangerousperson"},{"question":"To drive home","options":{"A":"Tofindone'sroots","B":"Toreturntoplaceofrest","C":"Backtooriginalposition","D":"Toemphasise","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Toemphasise"},{"question":"To have an axe to grind","options":{"A":"Aprivateendtoserve","B":"Tofailtoarouseinterest","C":"Tohavenoresult","D":"Toworkforbothsides","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Aprivateendtoserve"},{"question":"Sobhraj could be easily arrested because the police were tipped off in a advance.","options":{"A":"Toppledover","B":"Bribed","C":"Givenadvanceinformation","D":"Threatened"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Givenadvanceinformation"},{"question":"I met him after a long time, but he gave me the cold shoulder.","options":{"A":"scoldedme","B":"insultedme","C":"abusedme","D":"ignoredme"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ignoredme"},{"question":"He passed himself off as a noble man.","options":{"A":"Wasregardedas","B":"Pretendedtobe","C":"Wasthoughttobe","D":"Waslookedupon"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Pretendedtobe"},{"question":"This matter has been hanging fire for the last many months and must therefore be decided one way or the other.","options":{"A":"goingonslowly","B":"hotlydebated","C":"stuckup","D":"ignored"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"goingonslowly"},{"question":"In the armed forces, it is considered a great privilege to die in harness.","options":{"A":"dieonahorseback","B":"dieinthebattlefield","C":"diewhilestillworking","D":"diewithhonour"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"diewhilestillworking"},{"question":"The cricket match proved to be a big draw.","options":{"A":"akeencontest","B":"ahugeattraction","C":"alovelyspectacle","D":"agamewithoutanyresult"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"ahugeattraction"},{"question":"When he heard that he had once again not been selected he lost heart.","options":{"A":"becamedesperate","B":"feltsad","C":"becameangry","D":"becamediscouraged"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"becamediscouraged"},{"question":"He was undecided. He let the grass grow under his feet.","options":{"A":"loiteredaround","B":"stayedout","C":"satunmoving","D":"movedaway"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"loiteredaround"},{"question":"Although he has failed in the written examination, he is using backstairs influence to get the job.","options":{"A":"Politicalinfluence","B":"Backinginfluence","C":"Deservingandproperinfluence","D":"Secretandunfairinfluence"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Secretandunfairinfluence"}],"one-word-substitutes":[{"question":"Extreme old age when a man behaves like a fool","options":{"A":"Imbecility","B":"Senility","C":"Dotage","D":"Superannuation"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Dotage"},{"question":"That which cannot be corrected","options":{"A":"Unintelligible","B":"Indelible","C":"Illegible","D":"Incorrigible"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Incorrigible"},{"question":"The study of ancient societies","options":{"A":"Anthropology","B":"Archaeology","C":"History","D":"Ethnology"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Archaeology"},{"question":"A person of good understanding knowledge and reasoning power","options":{"A":"Expert","B":"Intellectual","C":"Snob","D":"Literate"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Intellectual"},{"question":"A person who insists on something","options":{"A":"Disciplinarian","B":"Stickler","C":"Instantaneous","D":"Boaster"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Stickler"},{"question":"State in which the few govern the many","options":{"A":"Monarchy","B":"Oligarchy","C":"Plutocracy","D":"Autocracy"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Oligarchy"},{"question":"A style in which a writer makes a display of his knowledge","options":{"A":"Pedantic","B":"Verbose","C":"Pompous","D":"Ornate"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Pedantic"}],"ordering-of-sentences":[{"question":"S1:In the middle of one side of the square sits the Chairman of the committee, the most important person in the room.P :For a committee is not just a mere collection of individuals.Q :On him rests much of the responsibility for the success or failure of the committee.R :While this is happening we have an opportunity to get the 'feel' of this committe.S :As the meeting opens, he runs briskly through a number of formalities.S6:From the moment its members meet, it begins to have a sort nebulous life of its own.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSQP","B":"PQRS","C":"SQPR","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:A force of exists between everybody in the universe.P :Normally it is very small but when the one of the bodies is a planet, like earth, the force is considerable.Q :It has been investigated by many scientists including Galileo and Newton.R :Everything on or near the surface of the earth is attracted by the mass of earth.S :This gravitational force depends on the mass of the bodies involved.S6:The greater the mass, the greater is the earth's force of attraction on it. We can call this force of attraction gravity.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRQS","B":"PRSQ","C":"QSRP","D":"QSPR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:Calcutta unlike other cities kepts its trams.P :As a result there horrendous congestion.Q :It was going to be the first in South Asia.R :They run down the centre of the roadS :To ease in the city decided to build an underground railway line.S6:The foundation stone was laid in 1972.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRSQ","B":"PSQR","C":"SQRP","D":"RPSQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:For some time in his youth Abraham Lincoln was manager for a shop.P :Then a chance Customer would come.Q :Young Lincoln way of keeping shop was entirely unlike anyone else'sR :Lincoln would jump up and attend to his needs and then revert to his reading.S :He used to lie full length on the counter of the shop eagerly reading a book.S6:Never before had Lincoln had so much time for reading as had then.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"QSPR","C":"SQRP","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:All the land was covered by the ocean.P :The leading god fought the monster, killed it and chopped its body in to two halves.Q :A terrible monster prevented the gods from separating the land from the water.R :The god made the sky out of the upper part of the body and ornamented it with stars.S :The god created the earth from the lower part, grew plants on it and populated it with animals.S6:The god moulded the first people out of clay according to his own image and mind.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"PQSR","C":"QPSR","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:Smoke oozed up between the planks.P :Passengers were told to be ready to quit the ship.Q :The rising gale fanned the smouldering fire.R :Everyone now knew there was fire on board.S :Flames broke out here and there.S6:Most people bore the shock bravely.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"QPSR","C":"RSPQ","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SRQP"},{"question":"S1:You know my wife, Madhavi, always urged me to give up smoking.P :I really gave it up.Q :And so When I went to jail I said to myself I really must give it up, if for no other reason than of being self-reliant.R :When I emerged from jail, I wanted to tell her of my great triumph.S :But when I met her, there she was with a packet of cigarettes.S6:poor girl!.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"SPQR","C":"QPRS","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:When a satellite is launched, the rocket begins by going slowly upwards through the air.P :However, the higher it goes, the less air it meets.Q :As the rocket goes higher, it travels faster.R :For the atmosphere becomes thinner.S :As a result there is less friction.S6:Consequently, the rocket still does not become too hot.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"QSPR","C":"PQRS","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:A father having offered to take the baby out in a perambulator, was tempted by the sunny morning to slip into a pub for a glass of beer.P :Indignant at her husband's behaviour, she decided to teach him a lesson.Q :She wheeled away the pram.R :A little later, his wife came by, where to her horror, she discovered her sleeping baby.S :Leaving the pram outside, he disappeared inside the bar.S6:She waited for him, anticipating the white face and quivering lips which would soon appear with the news that the baby had been stolen.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"RQPS","C":"SPQR","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SRPQ"},{"question":"S1:The city is almost a slum and stinks most of time.P :The slush on the road did not deter them.Q :The occasional slips and falls were considered a small price to pay for the trip.R :They were excited, fascinated by the sight of fresh snow on the roads.S :Even so, it looked beautiful to tourists of various categories.S6:But some visitors came away with the unforgettable sight of young labours scantily clad.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQPS","B":"QPRS","C":"RSQP","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"SPQR"},{"question":"S1:Venice is a strange and beautiful city in the north of Italy.P :There are about four hundred old stone bridges joining the island of Venice.Q :In this city there are no motor cars, no horses, no buses.R :These small islands are near one another.S :It is not an island but a hundred and seventeen islands.S6:This is because Venice has no streets.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"PRQS","C":"SRPQ","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SRPQ"},{"question":"S1:The Hound of Baskervilles was feared by the people of the area.P :Some people spoke of seeing a huge, shadowy form a Hound at midnight on the moor.Q :But they spoke of it in tones of horror.R :Nobody had actually seen the hound.S :This shadowy form did not reveal any details about the animal.S6:The Hound of Baskervilles remains an unsolved mystery.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPQR","B":"SPRQ","C":"PSRQ","D":"PQRS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"S1:A gentleman who lived alone always had two plates placed on the table at dinner time.P :One day just as he sat down to dine, the cat rushed in to the room.Q :One plate was for himself and other was for his cat.R :she drooped a mouse into her own plate and another into her master plate.S :He used to give the cat a piece of meat from his own plate.S6:In this way the cat showed her gratitude to her master.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QSPR","B":"PSRQ","C":"QRSP","D":"RPQS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:Ants eat worms, centipedes and spiders.P :They are usually much quicker than the ant itself.Q :Nevertheless, these animals do not make easy game for ants.R :Besides, they have an extraordinary number of ways of escaping.S :They also eat larvae and insect adults such as flies, moths and spring tails.S6:Some jump, and some give out a pungent repellent substance.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"SPRQ","C":"SQRP","D":"SRQP"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:Satyajit Ray made several films for children.P :Later film makers have followed his lead.Q :Today other nations are making the children's film in a big way.R :This was at a time when no director considered children as potential audience.S :Ray was, thus, a pioneer in the field.S6:But today few think of Ray as a maker of children's films.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"RSQP","C":"RSPQ","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RSPQ"},{"question":"S1:Hungary, with a population of about 10 million, lies between Czechoslovakia to the north and Yugoslavia to the south.P :Here a great deal of grain is grown.Q :In recent years, however, progress has been made also in the field of industrialisation.R :Most of this country consists of an extremely fertile plain, through which the river Danube flows.S :In addition to grain, the plain produces potatoes, sugar, wine and livestock.S6:The new industries derive mainly from agricultural production.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"RPSQ","C":"PRSQ","D":"RQSP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:Palaeobotany is the study of fossil plants preserved in rocks dating back in millions of years.P :Records of the history of the world are contained in fossils.Q :Through the ages, plants have evolved from simple to more complex forms.R :First there were water plants then land plants appeared during the Paleozoic era.S :But since the fossil remains appear locked in rock layers, they are closely related to the geologist area of investigation.S6:The fossil plants indicate the age of the rock, and also point to facts regarding climate, temperature and topography.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQSP","B":"SQRP","C":"PSQR","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"S1:On vacation in Tangier, Morocco, my friend and I sat down at a street cafe.P :At one point, he bent over with a big smile, showing me, a single gold tooth and a dingy fez.Q :soon I felt the presence of someone standing alongside me.R :But this one wouldn't budge.S :We had been cautioned about beggars and were told to ignore them.S6:Finally a man walked over to me and whispered, \"Hey buddy this guy is your waiter and he wants your order\"The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQRP","B":"SQPR","C":"QSRP","D":"QSPR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:And then Gandhi came.P :Get off the backs of these peasants and workers, he told us, all you who live by their exploitation.Q :He was like a powerful current of fresh air, like a beam of light, like a whirlwind that upset many things.R :He spoke their language and constantly dre their attention to their appalling conditions.S :He didn't descent from the top, he seemed to emerge from the masses of India.S6:Political freedom took new shape and then acquired a new content.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QSRP","B":"SRQP","C":"RSQP","D":"PRSQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SRQP"},{"question":"S1:Biological evolution has not fitted man to any specific environment.P :It is by no means a biological evolution, but it is a cultural one.Q :His imagination, his reason, his emotional subtlety and toughness, makes it possible for him not to accept the environment but to change.R :And that series of inventions by which man from age by age has reshaped his environment is a different kind of evolution.S :Among the multitude of animals which scamper, burrow swim around us he is in the only one who is not locked in to his environment.S6:That brilliant sequence of cultural peaks can most appropriately be termed the ascent of man.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"SRQP","C":"QRSP","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QRSP"},{"question":"S1:The dictionary is the best friend of you task.P :That may not be possible always.Q :It is wise to look it up immediately.R :Then it must be firmly written on the memory and traced at the first opportunity.S :Never allow a strange word to pass unchallenged.S6:soon you will realize that this is an exciting task.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"SPQR","C":"QRPS","D":"SQPR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:The Bhagavadgita recognises the nature of man and the needs of man.P :All these three aspects constitute the nature of man.Q :It shows how the human being is rational one, an ethical one and a spiritual one.R :More than all, it must be a spiritual experience.S :Nothing can give him fulfilment unless it satisfies his reason, his ethical conscience.S6:A man whom does not harmonise them, is not truly human.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"RSPQ","C":"QPSR","D":"PSQR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:I usually sleep quite well in the train, but this time I slept only a little.P :Most people wanted it shut and I wanted it open.Q :As usual, I got angry about the window.R :The quarrel left me completely upset.S :There were too many people too much huge luggage all around.S6:It was shut all night, as usualThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSQP","B":"SQPR","C":"SQRP","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:In 1934, William Golding published a small volume of poems.P :During the World War II(1939-45) he joined the Royal Navy and was present at the sinking of the Bismarck.Q :He returned to teaching in 1945 and gave it up in 1962, and is now a full time writer.R :In 1939, he married and started teaching at Vishop Wordsworth school in Salisbury.S :At first his novels were not accepted.S6:But the Lord of the files which came out in 1954 was welcomed as \"a most absorbing and instructive tale\".The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"RPSQ","C":"SRPQ","D":"SQPR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RPQS"},{"question":"S1:The future beckons to us.P :In fact we have hard work ahead.Q :Where do we go and what shall be our endeavour?R :We shall also have to fight and end poverty, ignorance and disease.S :It will be to bring freedom and oppurtunity to the common man.S6:There is no resting for any one of us till we redeem our pledge in full.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"QPSR","C":"QSRP","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:Most of the universities in the country are now facing financial crisis.P :Cost benefit yardstick thus should not be applied in the case of universities.Q :The current state of affairs cannot be allowed to continue for long.R :Universities cannot be equated with commercial enterprises.S :Proper development of universities and colleges must be ensured.S6:The Government should realise this before it is too late.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"QSPR","C":"QRSP","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"S1:While talking to a group, one should feel self-confident and courageous.P :Nor is it a gift bestowed by providence on only a few.Q :One should also learn how to think calmly and clearly.R :It is like the ability to play golf.S :It is not as difficult as most men imagine.S6:Any man can develop his capacity if he has  the desire to do so.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"QSPR","C":"QRSP","D":"RSQP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:A ceiling on urban property.P :No mill-owner could own factories or mills or plants.Q :And mass circulation papersR :Would mean thatS :No press magnate could own printing presses.S6:since their value would exceed the ceiling fixed by the government.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QSRP","B":"RPSQ","C":"SRPQ","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:The art of growing old is one which the passage of time has forced upon my attention.P :One of these is undue absorption in the past.Q :One's thought must be directed to the future and to things about which there is something to be done.R :Psychologically, there are two dangers to be guarded against in old age.S :It does not do to live in memories, in regrets for the good old days, or in sadness about friend who are dead.S6:This is not always easy one's own past is gradually increasing weight.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QSRP","B":"RPQS","C":"RPSQ","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:I keep on flapping my big ears all day.P :They also fear that I will flip them all away.Q :But children wonder why I flap them so.R :I flap them so to make sure they are safely there on either side of my head.S :But I know what I am doing.S6:Am I not a smart, intelligent elephant?The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"QPSR","C":"QPRS","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:Once King Shantnu met a young and beautiful fisher girl.P :He went to the fisherman and asked him for her asked him for her hand in marriage.Q :The King was extremely sad and returned to his palace.R :He fell in love with the fisher girl.S :The fisherman agreed to it condition that the son of his daughter should be heir to the throne of Hastinapur.S6:Devavrata, the King's son, asked him the reason of his sadness.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"RPSQ","C":"QSPR","D":"PSQR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:Reliogion is not a matter of mere dogmatic conformity.P :It is not merely going through the ritual prescribed to us.Q :It is not a question of ceremonial piety.R :Unless that kind of transformation occurs, you are not an authentically religious man.S :It is the remarking of your own self, the transformation of your nature.S6:A man of that character is free from fear, free from hatred.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPRQ","B":"QPSR","C":"PSRQ","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:We speak today of self-determination in politics.P :So long as one is conscious of a restraint, it is possible to resist it or to near it as a necessary evil and to keep free in spirit.Q :Slavery begins when one ceases to feel that restraint and it depends on if the evil is accepted as good.R :There is, however, a subtler domination exercised in the sphere of ideas by one culture to another.S :Political subjection primarily means restraint on the outer life of people.S6:Cultural subjection is ordinarily of an unconscious character and it implies slavery from the very start.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPRQ","B":"RSQP","C":"SPQR","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SPQR"},{"question":"S1:Once upon a time an ant lived on the bank of river.P :The dove saw the ant struggling in water in a helpless condition.Q :All its efforts to come up is failed.R :One day it suddenly slipped in to water.S :A dove lived in the tree on the bank not far from the spot.S6:She was touched.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQSP","B":"QRPS","C":"SRPQ","D":"PQRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"S1:The December dance and music season in Madras is like the annual tropical cyclone.P :A few among the new aspirants dazzle witht he colour of youth, like fresh saplings.Q :It rains an abundance of music for over a fortnight.R :Thick clouds expectation charge the atmosphere with voluminous advertisements.S :At the end of it one is left with the feeling that the music of only those artists seasoned by careful nurturing, stands tall like well-routed trees.S6:Many a hastily planed shrub gets washed away in the storm.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQPS","B":"QRPS","C":"RQSP","D":"QRSP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"S1:There is a touching story of Professor Hardy visiting Ramanujan as he lay desperately ill in hospital at Putney.P :'No Hardy, that is not a dull number in the very least.Q :Hardy, who was a very shy man, could not find the words for his distress.R :It was 1729.S :The best he could do, as he got to the beside was \"I say Ramanujan, I thought the number of taxi I came down in was a very dull number\"S6:It is the lowest number that can be expressed in two different ways as the sum of two cubes.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRSQ","B":"QSRP","C":"QSPR","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:Politeness is not a quality possessed by only one nation or race.P :One may observe that a man of one nation will remove his hat or fold his hands by way of greetings when he meets someone he knows.Q :A man of another country will not to do so.R :It is a quality to be found among all peoples and nations in every corner of the earth.S :Obviously, each person follows the custom of his particular country.S6:In any case, we should not mock at others habits.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"RPSQ","C":"PRQS","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:Throughout history man has used energy from the sun.P :Today, when we burn wood or use electric current we are drawing an energy.Q :However we now have a new supply of energy.R :All our ordinary life depends on sun.S :This has come from the sun.S6:This energy comes from inside atoms.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"RQPS","C":"QSRP","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"S1:This weather-vane often tops a church spire, tower or high building.P :They are only wind-vanes.Q :Neither alone can tell us what the weather will be.R :They are designed to point to direction from which the wind is coming.S :Just as the barometer only tells us the pressure of air, the weather-vane tells us the direction of wind.S6:The weather-vane can, however give us some indication of other.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"PSRQ","C":"PRSQ","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"SPQR"},{"question":"S1:But how does a new word get into the dictionary?P :When a new dictionary is being edited, a lexicographer collects all the alphabetically arranged citation slips for a particular word.Q :The dictionary makers notice it and make a note of it on a citation slip.R :The moment new word is coined, it usually enter the spoken language.S :The word then passes from the realm of hearing to the realm of writing.S6:He sorts them according to their grammatical function, and carefully writes a definition.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"PRSQ","C":"RQPS","D":"RSQP"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"PQRS"},{"question":"S1:Growing up means not only getting larger, but also using our sense and our brain is to become more aware of things around us.P :Not only does he have a memory but he is able to think and reason.Q :In this, man differs from all other animals.R :Before we spray our roadside plants or turn sewage in to our rivers, we should pause to think what the results of our action are likely to do.S :This is to say, he is able to plan what he is is going to do in the light of his experience before he does it.S6:In other words, we must develop and use our ability to reason, because the destruction or the preservation of the places in which we live depend on us.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"SPQR","C":"SPRQ","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:Jawaharlal Nehru was the greatest plan-enthusiast.P :Under Nehru's advice, the pre-Independent congress set up National Planning Commission in 1938.Q :But he forgot that what could be achieved by force under the communist dictatorship of Russia was not possible under the democratic set up of India.R :He took the idea from Russia where Five year plans transformed a very backward country into a top power of the world.S :No free government can call for compulsory sacrifice and suffering from the whole people.S6:Nehru himself became the chairman of the commission.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"SRQP","C":"QPRS","D":"RQSP"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"S1:Duryodhana was a wicked prince.P :one day Bhima made Duryodhana fall from a tree from which Duryodhana was stealing fruits.Q :He did not like that Pandavas should be loved and respected by the people of HastinapurR :Duryodhana specially hated Bhima.S :Among the Pandavas, Bhima was extraordinary strong and powerfulS6:This enraged Duryodhana so much that he began to think of removing Bhima from his way.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"QPRS","C":"QSPR","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:Jawaharlal Nehru was born in Allahabad on 14 Nov 1889.P :Nehru meet Mahatma Gandhi in February 1920.Q :In 1905 he was sent to London to study at a school called Haroow.R :He became the first Prime Minister of Independent India on 15 August 1947.S :He married Kamla Kaul in 1915.S6:He died on 27 May 1964.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"QSPR","C":"RPQS","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:It was a dark moonless night.P :He turned over the pages, reading passages here and there.Q :He heard them on the floor.R :The poet took down his books of poems from his shelves.S :Some of them contained his earliest writings which he had almost forgotten.S6:They all seemed to him to be poor and ordinary mere childish words.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"RQSP","C":"RSPQ","D":"RPSQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"S1:I had halted on the road.P :As soon as I saw the elephant I knew I should not shoot him.Q :It is a serious matter to shoot a working elephant.R :I knew that his 'must' was already passing off.S :The elephant was standing 8 yards from the road.S6:I decided to watch him for a while and then go home.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPQR","B":"PQSR","C":"RQPS","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"PQSR"},{"question":"S1:There is only one monkey we can thoroughly recommend as an indoor pet.P :They quickly die from colds and coughs after the first winter fogs.Q :It is beautiful and intelligent Capuchin monkey.R :The lively little Capuchins, however, may be left for years in an English house without the least danger to their health.S :The Marmosets, it is true, are more beautiful than a Capuchins and just as pleasing, but they are too delicate for the English climateS6:Finally let me say that no other monkey has a better temper or winning ways.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"QRPS","C":"QSPR","D":"RPSQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"S1:A man can be physically confined within stone walls.P :But his mind and spirit will still be free.Q :Thus his freedom of action may be restricted.R :His hopes and aspiration still remain with him.S :Hence, he will be free spiritually if not physically.S6:No tyranny can intimidate a lover of liberty.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"SRQP","C":"QPRS","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"PQRS"},{"question":"S1:Once upon atime there lived three young men in a certain town of Hindustan.P :All the people of the neighbourhood were mortally afraid of them.Q :They were so powerful that they could catch growing lions and tear them to pieces.R :Someone told them that they would become immortal if they killed Death.S :The young men believed themselves to be very good friends.S6:All of them set out in search of their foe called Death.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"SQPR","C":"RSQP","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:Metals are today being replaced by polymers in many applications.P :Above all, they are cheaper and easier to process making them a viable alternative to metals.Q :Polymers are essentially a long chains of hydrocarbon molecules.R :Today polymers as strong as metals have been developed.S :These have replaced the traditional chromium-plated metallic bumpers in cars.S6:Many Indian Institutes of science and Technology run special programmes on polymer science.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"RSQP","C":"RQSP","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QRSP"},{"question":"S1:Since the sixties there has been an increasing interest in neurophysiology, which deals with the neural bases of mental activity and behaviour.P :It has format which is very similar to that of Brain and Language, a sister journal.Q :Since then, a number of journals devoted entirely to this area of research have appeared.R :Before the 1960's when this field was the concern of a small number of investigators, research articles were scattered in various neurological journals.S :Brain and cognition is one such journal.S6:So far the journal has published the mixture of articles including reports and investigations.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQSP","B":"QRSP","C":"QSPR","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"S1:An elderly lady suddenly became blind.P :The doctor called daily and every time he took away some of her furniture he liked.Q :At last she was cured and the doctor demanded his fee.R :She agreed to pay a large fee to the doctor who would cure herS :On being refused, the doctor wanted to know the reason.S6:The lady said that she had not been properly cured because she could not see all his furniture.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"RPQS","C":"RSPQ","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RPQS"},{"question":"S1:What are the causes of our chronic food shortage ?P :To find for these growing new millions is desperate task.Q :every year, we add more than a crore of persons to our population.R :Despite stupendous efforts by our government, the population is growing unabated.S :The chief cause is the population explosion.S6:This unprecedented growth can drag us to the doors of starvation very soon.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"SQPR","C":"QPRS","D":"PSQR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:Our ancestors thought that anything which moved itself was alive.P :The philosopher Descartes thought that both men and animals were machines.Q :But a machine such as a motorcar or a steamship moves itself, as soon as machines which moved themselves had been made, people asked \"Is man a machine?\"R :And before the days of machinery that was a good definition.S :He also thought that the human machine was partly controlled by the soul action on a certain part of the brain, while animals had no souls.S6:Therefore some scientists think that life is just a very complicated mechanism.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRSQ","B":"RPQS","C":"PSQR","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"PSQR"},{"question":"S1:Payment for imports and exports is made through a system called foreign exchange.P :The value of the money of one country in relation to the money of other countries is agreed upon.Q :These rates of exchange vary from time to time.R :For instance, an American dollar or a British pound sterling is worth certain amounts in the money of other countries.S :Sometimes a United States dollar is worth 12 pesos in Mexico.S6:Another time it may be worth eight pesos.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"QPRS","C":"PRQS","D":"RPQS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"PRQS"},{"question":"S1:Moncure Conway devoted his life to two great objects freedom of thought, and freedom of the individual.P :They threaten both kinds of freedom.Q :But something also has been lost.R :There are now dangers, somewhat different in form from those of the past ages.S :In regard to both these objects, something has been gained since his time.S6:Unless a vigorous and vigilant public opinion can be aroused in defence of them, there will be much less of both a hundred years hence then there is now.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"QSPR","C":"SQRP","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SQRP"},{"question":"S1:The study of speech disorders due to brain injury suggests that patients can think without having adequate control over their language.P :But they succeed in playing games of chess.Q :Some patients, for example fail to find the names of objects presented to them.R :They can even use the concepts needed for chess playing, though they are unable to express many of the concepts in ordinary language.S :They even find it difficult to interpret long written notices.S6:How they manage to do this we do not know.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"RPSQ","C":"QSPR","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:A black haired, young woman came tripping along.P :She was leading a young woman wearing a hat.Q :The woman swept it off and tossed it in the air.R :The child jumped up to catch the hat.S :The young man tossed his head to shake the hat back.S6:Both disappeared from view.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"RPSQ","C":"QRPS","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"PSQR"},{"question":"S1:We now know that the oceans are very deep.P :For example, the Indian ocean has a range called the Indian Ridge.Q :Much of it is fairly flat.R :However, there are great mountain ranges as well.S :On average the bottom is 2.5 miles to 3.5 miles downS6:This reaches from the India to the Antarctic.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"PQSR","C":"RSQP","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:Minnie went shopping one morning.P :Disappointed She turned around and returned to the parking lot.Q :She got out and walked to the nearest shop.R :She drove her car into the parking lot and stopped.S :It was there that she realised that she'd forgotten her purse at home.S6:She drove home with an empty basket.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSQP","B":"RQSP","C":"PQRS","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"S1:Far away in a little street there is a poor house.P :Her face is thin and worn and her hands are coarse, pricked by a needle, for she is a seam stress.Q :One of the windows is open and through it I can see a poor woman.R :He has a fever and asking for oranges.S :In a bed in a corner of the room her little boy is lying ill.S6:His mother has nothing to give but water, so he is crying.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"PQSR","C":"QPSR","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:A noise started above their heads.P :But people did not take it seriously.Q :That was to show everyone that there was something wrongR :It was a dangerous thing to do.S :For, within minutes the ship began to sink.S6:Nearly 200 lives were lost on the fateful day.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQSR","B":"PRQS","C":"QPRS","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:American private lies may seem shallow.P :Students would walk away with books they had not paid for.Q :A Chinese journalist commented on a curious institution: the libraryR :Their public morality, however, impressed visitors.S :But in general they returned them.S6:This would not happen in china, he said.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"QPSR","C":"RQPS","D":"RPSQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"S1:The path of Venus lies inside the path of the Earth.P :When at its farthest from the Earth, Venus is 160 million awayQ :With such a wide range between its greatest and leat distances it is natural that at sometimes Venus appears much brighter than at others.R :No other body ever comes so near the Earth, with the exception of the Moon and occasional comet or asteroid.S :When Venus is at its nearest to the earth it is only 26 million miles away.S6:When at its brightest, it is easily seen with the naked eye in broad daylight.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"SQRP","C":"PSQR","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SRPQ"},{"question":"S1:In India marriages are usually arranged by parentsP :Sometimes boys and girls do not like th idea of arranged marriages.Q :Most young people accepts the state of affairs.R :Shanta was like that.S :They assume their parents can make good choices.S6:She felt she was a modern girl and not subject for bargaining.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPRQ","B":"PSRQ","C":"QSPR","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:She said on the phone that she would report for duty next day.P :We waited for few days then we decided to go to her place.Q :But she did not.R :we found it locked.S :Even after that we waited for her quite a few days.S6:Eventually we reported to the police.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRSQ","B":"QPSR","C":"QPRS","D":"SQPR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:Several sub-cities have been planned around capital.P :Dwarga is the first among them.Q :They are expected to alleviate the problem of housing.R :It is coming up in the south west of capital.S :It will cater to over one million people when completed.S6:Hopefully the housing problem will not be as acute at present after these sub-cities are built.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"PRSQ","C":"PQRS","D":"QRSP"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:Forecasting the weather has always been a difficult business.P :During a period of drought, streams and rivers dried up, the cattle died from thirst and were ruined.Q :Many different things affect the weather and we have to study them carefully to make accurate forecast.R :Ancient Egyptians had no need of weather in the  Nile Valley hardly ever changes.S :In early times, when there were no instruments, such as thermometer or the barometer, man looked for tell-tale signs in the sky.S6:He made his forecasts by watching flights of the birds or the way smoke rose from fire.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRQS","B":"QPRS","C":"QRPS","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"S1:As he passed beneath her he heard the swish of her wings.P :He was not falling head long now.Q :The monstrous terror seized him.R :But it only lasted a minute.S :He could hear nothing.S6:The next moment he felt his wings spread outwards.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"QSPR","C":"QSRP","D":"PRQS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:Ms. Parasuram started a Petrol Pump in Madras.P :A total to 12 girls now work at the pump.Q :She advertised in newspapers for women staff.R :They operate in 2 shifts.S :The response was good.S6:Thus she has shown the way for many others.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQSR","B":"SQPR","C":"QSPR","D":"PQRS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:Sun birds are among the smallest of Indian birds.P :Though they are functionally similar to the humming birds of the New World, they are totally unrelated.Q :They do eat insects too.R :They are also some of the most brilliantly coloured birds.S :sun birds feed on nectar mostly and helped in pollination.S6:Our common sun birds are the purple sun bird, the glossy black species and purple rumped sun bird, the yellow and maroon species.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"RPSQ","C":"QPRS","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1:For decades, American society has been calling a melting potP :Differences remained - in appearence, mannerisms, customs, speech, religion and more.Q :The term has long been a cliche and half-truth.R :But homogenisation was never acheived.S :Yes, immigrants from diverse cultures and traditions did cast off vestiges of their native lands and become almost imperceptibly woven in to the American fabric.S6:In recent years, such differences accentuated by the arrival of immigrants from Asia and other parts of the world in the United States - have become something to celebrate and to nurture.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"SQRP","C":"SQPR","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQRP"},{"question":"S1:I took cigarettes from my case.P :But when the fit of coughing was over, he replaced it between his lips.Q :I lit one of them and placed it between the lips.R :Then with a feeble hand he removed the cigarette.S :Slowly he took a pull at it and coughed violently.S6:Then he continues to draw on it.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"QPSR","C":"QSRP","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:There is difference between Gandhiji's concept of secularism and that of Nehru's.P :Nehru's idea of secularism was equal indifference to all religions and bothering about none of them.Q :According to Gandhiji, all religions are equally true and each scripture is worthy of respect.R :Such secularism which means the rejection of all religions is contrary to our culture and tradition.S :In Gandhiji's view, secularism stands for equal respect for all religions.S6:Instead of doing any good, such secularism can do harm instead of good.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"PSQR","C":"QSPR","D":"PRSQ"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"S1: As a dramatist Rabindranath was not what might be called a success.P :His dramas were moulded on the lines of the traditional Indian village dramas than the dramas of modern world.Q :His plays were more a catalogue of ideas than a vehicle of the expression of action.R :Actually the drama has always been the life of Indian people, as it deals with legends of gods and goddesses.S :Although in his short stories and novels he was able to create living and well defined characters, he did not seem to be able to do so in dramasS6:Therefor, drama forms the essential part of the traditional Indian Culture.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"QPSR","C":"QSPR","D":"RSQP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"S1:It is regrettable that there is widespread corruption in the country at all levels.P :So there is hardly anything that the government can do about it now.Q :And there are graft and other malpractices too.R :The impression that corruption is universal phenomenon persists and the people not cooperate in checking this evil.S :Recently several offenders were brought to book, but they were not given deterrent punishment.S6:This is indeed a tragedy of great magnitude.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QSRP","B":"SQRP","C":"RSQP","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"S1:The heart is pump of life.P :They have even succeeded in heart transplants.Q :Nowadays surgeons are able to stop a patients heart and carry out complicated operations.R :A few years ago it was impossible to operate on a patient whose heart was not working properly.S :If heart stops we die in about five minutes.S6:All this was made possible by the invention of heart-lung machine.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"SPRQ","C":"SQPR","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"SRQP"},{"question":"S1:Your letter was big relief.P :How did you exams go?Q :After your result, you must come here for a week.R :You hadn't written for over a month.S :I am sure you will come out with flying colours.S6:But don't forget to bring chocolate for Geetha.The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"QRPS","C":"RPSQ","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RPSQ"}],"ordering-of-words":[{"question":"When heP : did not knowQ : he was nervous andR : heard the hue and cry at midnightS : what to doThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQPS","B":"QSPR","C":"SQPR","D":"PQRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RQPS"},{"question":"It has been established thatP : Einstein wasQ : although a great scientistR : weak in arithmeticS : right from his school daysThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"QPRS","C":"QPSR","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"ThenP : it struck meQ : of courseR : suitable it wasS : how eminentlyThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPQR","B":"QSRP","C":"PSRQ","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"I read an advertisement that saidP : posh, air-conditionedQ : gentleman of tasteR : are available for S : fully furnished roomsThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"PSRQ","C":"PSQR","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"Since the beginning of history P : have managed to catch  Q : the Eskimos and Red Indians R : by a very difficulty method S : a few specimens of this aquatic animal The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"SQPR","C":"SQRP","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"A French womanP : committed suicideQ : where she had put upR : who had come to CalcuttaS : by jumping from the first floor balcony of the hotelThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRQS","B":"QSRP","C":"RPSQ","D":"SRQP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"The national unity of a free peopleP : to make it impracticableQ : for there to be an arbitrary administrationR : depends upon a sufficiently even balance of political powerS : against a revolutionary opposition that is irreconcilably opposed to itThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"QRSP","C":"RPQS","D":"RSPQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"RSPQ"},{"question":"The grocerP : did not listen to the protests of customerQ : who was in the habit of weighing lessR : whom he had cheatedS : with great audacityThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PRSQ","B":"QSPR","C":"QPRS","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"They felt safer P : to watch the mountain Q : of more than five miles R : as they settled down S : from a distance The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPSQ","B":"RSQP","C":"PQSR","D":"PRSQ"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"People P : at his dispensary Q : went to him R : of all professions S : for medicine and treatment The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"RPQS","C":"RQSP","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"If you need help P : promptly and politely Q : ask for attendants R : to help our customers S : who have instructions The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"QPSR","C":"QSRP","D":"SQRP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"It is easier P : to venture into spaceQ : for menR : beneath their feetS : than to exploreThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"QPSR","C":"PSRQ","D":"PQSR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"It was to be P : before their school examination Q : which was due to start R : the last expedition S : in a month's The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"RQSP","C":"RPQS","D":"SPRQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RPQS"},{"question":"This timeP : exactly what he had been toldQ : the young man didR : beyond his dreamsS : and the plan succeededThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"QPSR","C":"PQSR","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"In the darknessP : the long, narrow beardQ : was clearly visible withR : the tall stooping figure of the doctorS : and the aquiline noseThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQPS","B":"PSQR","C":"RSQP","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RQPS"},{"question":"We have toP : as we see it Q : speak the truthR : there is falsehood and weaknessS : even if all around usThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQSP","B":"QRPS","C":"RSQP","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"When it began to rain suddenly on the first of January P : to celebrate the new year Q : we ran for shelter R : to the neighbouring house S : where many people had gathered The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRPS","B":"PSQR","C":"PRSQ","D":"QRSP"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QRSP"},{"question":"He told us thatP : and enjoyed it immenselyQ : in a prose translationR : he had read MiltonS : which he had borrowed from his teacherThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSQP","B":"QRPS","C":"RQSP","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"He knew thatP : and then to save himselfQ : was to save all the livesR : entrusted to his careS : the duty of a captainThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"SQRP","C":"SPRQ","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQRP"},{"question":"It is not, thereforeP : that I pay a tributeQ : to conductors as a classR : with any feeling of unfriendlinessS : to a particular member of that classThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"RQPS","C":"RSPQ","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RSPQ"},{"question":"Of many artistsP : those who impressed me the mostQ : I was a childR : but those with unique personalities off stageS : were not always the successful onesThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRQP","B":"QRSP","C":"RSPQ","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"As a diseaseP : and breaks up marriagesQ : accidents and suicidesR : alcoholism leads toS : affecting all agesThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"RPSQ","C":"SRQP","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SRQP"},{"question":"It is easy to excuse P :but it is hard Q :in a boy of fourteen  R :the mischief of early childhood S :to tolerate even unavoidable faults  The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"QRSP","C":"QRPS","D":"RPSQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"The majestic mahogany tableP : belongs to an old princeQ : which has one leg missingR : who is no impoverishedS : but not without some prideThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQSR","B":"QRSP","C":"PRSQ","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"Education isP : of the proper sense of responsibilities Q : the first needR : in a citizenS : for the developmentThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQPR","B":"QSRP","C":"QSPR","D":"PQRS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSPR"},{"question":"It wouldP : appear from his statementQ : about the policy of managementR : in dealing with the strikeS : that he was quite in the darkThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPSQ","B":"PSQR","C":"RQPS","D":"PRQS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"PSQR"},{"question":"He was so kind and generous that P : he not only Q : made others do so R : but also S : helped them himself The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSRQ","B":"SPQR","C":"PRSQ","D":"QPRS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"We wentP : along the railway lineQ : and had a right toR : where other people not allowed to goS : but daddy belonged to the railwayThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"PRSQ","C":"RSQP","D":"PRQS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"PRSQ"},{"question":"There wasP : needed for it everyday lifeQ : a time when each familyR : for itself most of the things itS : actually producedThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QRSP","B":"RQPS","C":"RSPQ","D":"QSRP"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QSRP"},{"question":"LittleP : that he had been let downQ : stood by all these yearsR : did he realiseS : by a colleague whom he hadThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPSQ","B":"RSQP","C":"QSRP","D":"QSPR"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RPSQ"},{"question":"I saw that P : but seeing my host in this mood Q : I deemed it proper to take leave R : as I had frequently done before S : it had been my intention to pass the night there The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPSR","B":"QRPS","C":"SPQR","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"SRPQ"},{"question":"It is very easyP : a great deal more than one realisesQ : may meanR : that a phrase that one does not quite understandS : to persuade oneselfThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSQP","B":"SPQR","C":"SRQP","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SPQR"},{"question":"I wasP : and stay fro few days in DelhiQ : when my father told meR : very excitedS : that I could go with himThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"RQSP","C":"QRSP","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RQSP"},{"question":"work is the one thingP : and without itQ : that is necessaryR : to keep the world goingS : we should all dieThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPSR","B":"RPQS","C":"SRPQ","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"The appearance P : this dinosaurs were at their peak Q : of the first mammals on the earth R : at the time whenS : went almost unnoticedThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"QSRP","C":"QRPS","D":"RPQS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QRPS"},{"question":"By this timeP : at the railway stationQ : reported mass lootingR : reports of violence were flooding inS : which police dispatchesThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RSPQ","B":"SPRQ","C":"SQRP","D":"RSQP"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SQRP"},{"question":"Then the womenP :lamenting their evil desire Q :that had brought R :wept loudlyS :this sorrow upon them The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPQS","B":"RQPS","C":"PQSR","D":"PRQS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"RPQS"},{"question":"WomenP : till the other dayQ : who were content being housewivesR : about spending their time cookingS : now sound apologeticThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"RSPQ","C":"QPSR","D":"RQPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"Though he dialled frequentlyP : on telephoneQ : my brother could not contact meR : and had left no informationS : as I had gone out of officeThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPRS","B":"SQRP","C":"QPSR","D":"SPQR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"He saidP : here is the catQ : throughout the nightR : which had been paying havoc with thingsS : that ate the ratThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PSQR","B":"PSRQ","C":"QPRS","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"PSRQ"},{"question":"He satP : through the Town Hall ParkQ : which flanked a path runningR : under the boughsS : of a spreading tamarind treeThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQSR","B":"RSQP","C":"RSPQ","D":"PRSQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"RSQP"},{"question":"I don't remember P : I saw a man dying in front of a hospital  Q : but when I left lucknow in 1984 R : hit apparently by a fast moving car S : the exact date The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SQRP","B":"SQPR","C":"QRPS","D":"SPRQ"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SQPR"},{"question":"It wasP : in keeping with my moodQ : a soft summer eveningR : as I walked sedatelyS : in the direction of new houseThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SRPQ","B":"QRPS","C":"QPRS","D":"SQPR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"All such studentsP : get successQ : who are honest and hard-workingR : and recognitionS : in very walk of lifeThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"SPRQ","B":"PRQS","C":"QPRS","D":"PSRQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPRS"},{"question":"The master P : who was very loyal to him Q : punished the servant R : without giving any valid reason S : when he left the work unfinished The Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RQPS","B":"RQSP","C":"QPSR","D":"QRPS"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"With her bodyP : dragging her unwilling feetQ : weak and infirmR : doubled with ageS : she persisted in her missionThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"PQRS","B":"QPRS","C":"RQPS","D":"SRPQ"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"RQPS"},{"question":"P: We must readP : if we want to absorb the fruits of great literatureQ : but with concentrationR : them not as we do cricket storiesS :undefinedThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"QPSR","B":"PSQR","C":"PRSQ","D":"PRQS"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"QPSR"},{"question":"I encloseP : and the postageQ : a postal orderR : the price of booksS : which will coverThe Proper sequence should be:","options":{"A":"RPSQ","B":"QSPR","C":"QSRP","D":"QPSR"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"QSRP"}],"paragraph-formation":[{"question":"Which sentence should come third in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which sentence should come last in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fourth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which sentence should come second in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which sentence should come first in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fourth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which sentence should come third in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which sentence should come second in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fifth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which sentence should come first in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which sentence should come third in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which sentence should come first in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fifth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fourth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which sentence should come second in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the fourth sentence in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the last sentence in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the third sentence in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the second sentence in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the first sentence in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which sentence should come sixth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"5","B":"4","C":"2","D":"1","E":"3"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which sentence should come third in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"2","B":"5","C":"1","D":"4","E":"6"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which sentence should come second in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"3","B":"1","C":"4","D":"6","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which sentence should come fourth in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"6","B":"3","C":"5","D":"2","E":"1"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"6"},{"question":"Which sentence should come first in the paragraph?","options":{"A":"4","B":"6","C":"3","D":"2","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the third sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the first sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the second sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the sixth sentence ?","options":{"A":"6","B":"5","C":"4","D":"3","E":"2"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the fourth sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"6","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"6"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the first sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the second sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the fourth sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the third sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the fifth sentence ?","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4","E":"5"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"5"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the third sentence ?","options":{"A":"6","B":"5","C":"4","D":"3","E":"2"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"4"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the first sentence ?","options":{"A":"6","B":"5","C":"4","D":"3","E":"2"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"3"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the sixth sentence ?","options":{"A":"6","B":"5","C":"4","D":"3","E":"2"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"6"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the fourth sentence ?","options":{"A":"5","B":"4","C":"3","D":"2","E":"1"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"2"},{"question":"Which of the following should be the second sentence ?","options":{"A":"6","B":"5","C":"4","D":"3","E":"2"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"5"}],"selecting-words":[{"question":"Fate smiles ...... those who untiringly grapple with stark realities of life.","options":{"A":"with","B":"over","C":"on","D":"round"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"on"},{"question":"The miser gazed ...... at the pile of gold coins in front of him.","options":{"A":"avidly","B":"admiringly","C":"thoughtfully","D":"earnestly"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"avidly"},{"question":"Catching the earlier train will give us the ...... to do some shopping.","options":{"A":"chance","B":"luck","C":"possibility","D":"occasion"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"chance"},{"question":"I saw a ...... of cows in the field.","options":{"A":"group","B":"herd","C":"swarm","D":"flock"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"herd"},{"question":"The grapes are now ...... enough to be picked.","options":{"A":"ready","B":"mature","C":"ripe","D":"advanced"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"ripe"},{"question":"Success in this examination depends ...... hard work alone.","options":{"A":"at","B":"over","C":"for","D":"on"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"on"},{"question":"My uncle decided to take ...... and my sister to the market.","options":{"A":"I","B":"mine","C":"me","D":"myself"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"me"},{"question":"If you smuggle goods into the country, they may be ...... by the customs authority.","options":{"A":"possessed","B":"punished","C":"confiscated","D":"fined"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"confiscated"},{"question":"Man does not live by ...... alone.","options":{"A":"food","B":"bread","C":"meals","D":"diet"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"bread"},{"question":"Piyush behaves strangely at times and, therefore, nobody gets ...... with him.","options":{"A":"about","B":"through","C":"along","D":"up"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"along"},{"question":"Rohan and Rohit are twin brothers, but they do not look ......","options":{"A":"unique","B":"different","C":"likely","D":"alike"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"alike"},{"question":"To err is ...... to forgive divine.","options":{"A":"beastly","B":"human","C":"inhuman","D":"natural"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"human"},{"question":"The ruling party will have to put its own house ...... order.","options":{"A":"in","B":"on","C":"to","D":"into"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"in"}],"sentence-correction":[{"question":"The small child does whatever his father was done.","options":{"A":"hasdone","B":"did","C":"does","D":"haddone","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"does"},{"question":"You need not come unless you want to.","options":{"A":"Youdon'tneedtocomeunlessyouwantto","B":"Youcomeonlywhenyouwantto","C":"Youcomeunlessyoudon'twantto","D":"Youneedn'tcomeuntilyoudon'twantto","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Youdon'tneedtocomeunlessyouwantto"},{"question":"There are not many men who are so famous that they are frequently referred to by their short names only","options":{"A":"initials","B":"signatures","C":"pictures","D":"middlenames","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"initials"},{"question":"The man to who I sold my house was a cheat.","options":{"A":"towhomIsell","B":"towhoIsell","C":"whowassoldto","D":"towhomIsold","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"towhomIsold"},{"question":"They were all shocked at his failure in the competition.","options":{"A":"wereshockedatall","B":"hadallshockedat","C":"hadallshockedby","D":"hadbeenallshockedon","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"I need not offer any explanation regarding this incident - my behaviour is speaking itself.","options":{"A":"willspeaktoitself","B":"speaksforitself","C":"hasbeenspeaking","D":"speaksaboutitself","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"speaksforitself"},{"question":"He is too important for tolerating any delay.","options":{"A":"totolerate","B":"totolerating","C":"attolerating","D":"withtolerating","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"totolerate"},{"question":"The population of Tokyo is greater than that of any other town in the world.","options":{"A":"greatestamonganyother","B":"greaterthanallother","C":"greaterthanthoseofanyother","D":"greaterthananyother","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The performance of our players was rather worst than I had expected.","options":{"A":"badasIhadexpected","B":"worsethanIhadexpected","C":"worsethanexpectation","D":"worstthanwasexpected","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"worsethanIhadexpected"},{"question":"Why did you not threw the bag away?","options":{"A":"didyounotthrow","B":"hadyounotthrew","C":"didyounotthrown","D":"youdidnotthrown","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"didyounotthrow"},{"question":"Shapes of gods and goddess are worshipped by people.","options":{"A":"Images","B":"Reflections","C":"Clayshapes","D":"Claytoys","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Images"},{"question":"In addition to enhanced their reputations through strategic use of philanthropy, companies are sponsoring  social initiatives to open new markets.","options":{"A":"ofenhancingtheirreputation","B":"tohavingenhancetheirreputation","C":"toenhancingtheirreputation","D":"tohavetheirreputationenhancing","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"toenhancingtheirreputation"},{"question":"The intruder stood quietly for few moments","options":{"A":"forfewtime","B":"forthefewmoments","C":"formoments","D":"forafewmoments","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"forafewmoments"},{"question":"The police has so far succeeded in recovering only a part of the stolen property.","options":{"A":"thusfarsucceededforrecovery","B":"sofarsucceededinrecoveryof","C":"asforassucceededinrecoveryof","D":"sofarsucceededtorecover","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"He confidentially asked the crowd if they thought he was right and the crowd shouted that they did.","options":{"A":"thathedid","B":"thattheyhad","C":"thatheis","D":"thathedidn't","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"Why should the candidates be afraid of English Language is not clear.","options":{"A":"thecandidatesshouldbe","B":"dothecandidatesbe","C":"shouldbethecandidates","D":"arethecandidates","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"thecandidatesshouldbe"},{"question":"He found the gold coin as he cleans the floor.","options":{"A":"ashehadcleaned","B":"whilehecleans","C":"whichheiscleaning","D":"whilecleaning","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"whilecleaning"},{"question":"He admired the speed with which he completed the work and appreciating the method adopted by him","options":{"A":"appreciatethemethodbeingadopted","B":"appreciatedthemethodadopted","C":"appreciatethemethodofadoption","D":"appreciatedthemethodadoptingmethod","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"appreciatedthemethodadopted"},{"question":"Maria unnecessarily picked up a quarrel with Rani and left the party hurried.","options":{"A":"haspickedup","B":"pickedon","C":"picked","D":"pickingup","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"picked"},{"question":"She cooks, washes dishes, does her homework and then relaxing.","options":{"A":"relaxingthen","B":"thenisrelaxing","C":"relaxingisthen","D":"thenrelaxes","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"thenrelaxes"},{"question":"Acquisition of certain specific skills can be facilitated from general awareness, education to novel situations","options":{"A":"canbefacilitatedby","B":"mayfacilitatethrough","C":"canbefelicitatedwith","D":"maybefelicitatedwith","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"canbefacilitatedby"},{"question":"He never has and ever will take such strong measures.","options":{"A":"hadtakennorwillevertake","B":"hadtakenandwillevertake","C":"hasandneverwilltake","D":"hadandeverwilltake","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"hadtakennorwillevertake"},{"question":"Technology must use to feed the forces of change.","options":{"A":"mustbeusedtofeed","B":"musthavebeenusingtofeed","C":"mustusehavingfed","D":"mustbeusingtofeed","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"mustbeusedtofeed"},{"question":"Anyone interested in the use of computers can learn much if you have access to a personal computer.","options":{"A":"theyhaveaccess","B":"accesscanbeavailable","C":"heorshehasaccess","D":"oneofthemhaveaccess","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"heorshehasaccess"},{"question":"They are not beware of all the facts","options":{"A":"arenotawarefor","B":"arenotawareof","C":"arenottobeaware","D":"mustnottobeawarefor","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"arenotawareof"},{"question":"We can not always convey ourselves in simple sentences.","options":{"A":"cannotalwaysconvey","B":"cannotalwaysexpress","C":"cannotalwaysexpress","D":"cannotalwayscommunicate","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"cannotalwaysexpress"},{"question":"What does agonise me most is not this criticism, but the trivial reason behind it.","options":{"A":"mostagonisingme","B":"agonisesmemost","C":"agonisingmemost","D":"Imostagonised","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"agonisesmemost"},{"question":"As there was no time, the remaining items were deferred into the next meeting.","options":{"A":"aredeferredtill","B":"weredeferredtill","C":"weredeferredto","D":"haddeferredwith","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"weredeferredtill"},{"question":"Despite of their differences on matters of principles, they all agree on the demand of hike is salary?","options":{"A":"Despitetheir","B":"Despiteofthe","C":"Despitefortheir","D":"Despiteofftheir","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Despitetheir"},{"question":"The man who has committed such a serious crime must get the mostly severe punishment.","options":{"A":"begettingthemostlyseverely","B":"getthemostsevere","C":"havegotthemostseverely","D":"havebeengettingtheseveremost","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"getthemostsevere"},{"question":"For many centuries in Indian History there was no city so famous like the city of Ujjain.","options":{"A":"as","B":"suchas","C":"likewise","D":"solike","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"as"},{"question":"We don't know how did the thief made an escape.","options":{"A":"howthethiefdidmake","B":"howthethiefdoesmake","C":"howthethiefmade","D":"howwasthethiefmade","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"howthethiefmade"},{"question":"He is a singer of repute, but his yesterday's performance was quite disappointing.","options":{"A":"performancesofyesterdaywere","B":"yesterdayperformancewas","C":"yesterdayperformancewere","D":"performancesaboutyesterdaywere","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"Their earnings are such that they find it difficult to make both ends to meet.","options":{"A":"tomakingsbothendsmeet","B":"tomakebothendsformeeting","C":"tomakebothendsmeet","D":"formakingbothendstomeet","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"tomakebothendsmeet"},{"question":"He has received no other message than an urgent telegram asking him to rush his village immediately.","options":{"A":"askedhimtorushhisvillage","B":"askinghimtohaverushhisvillage","C":"askinghimtorushtohisvillage","D":"askinghimrushingathisvillage","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"askinghimtorushtohisvillage"},{"question":"One of the most significant phenomenons of our time has been the development of cinema.","options":{"A":"phenomenon","B":"phenomena","C":"phenomenonna","D":"phenomenonns","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"phenomena"},{"question":"Had you been told me about your problem, I would have helped you.","options":{"A":"Ifyouwouldhavetold","B":"Hadyouhavetold","C":"hadyoutold","D":"Ifyouhavetold","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"hadyoutold"},{"question":"It was until many years later that Gandhi became a rebel against authority.","options":{"A":"Itwasnotuntilmanyyears","B":"Itwastillmanyyears","C":"Itwasnotmanyyears","D":"UntilItwasmanyyears","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Itwasnotuntilmanyyears"},{"question":"Anand has the guts to rise from the occasion and come out successfully.","options":{"A":"inrisingfrom","B":"toraisewith","C":"toriseto","D":"toriseagainst","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"toriseto"},{"question":"If you are thinking about investigation overseas, isn't it makes sense to find an experience guide?","options":{"A":"itisnotmaking","B":"doesn'titmake","C":"doesitmake","D":"isitmaking","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"doesn'titmake"},{"question":"This is one of the most important inventions of this century.","options":{"A":"inventionofthiscentury","B":"inventionofthesecentury","C":"inventionofcenturies","D":"inventionofthecenturies","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The orator had been left the auditorium before the audience stood up.","options":{"A":"hadbeenleaving","B":"wasleft","C":"hadleft","D":"wouldleave","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"hadleft"},{"question":"He dislikes the word dislike, isn't he","options":{"A":"didn'the","B":"doesn'the","C":"hasn'the","D":"doeshe","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"doesn'the"},{"question":"We must take it granted that Madhu will not come for today's function.","options":{"A":"takeitforgranted","B":"takingitgranted","C":"tookitasgranted","D":"haveitgranted","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"takeitforgranted"},{"question":"The research study is an eye-opener and attempts to acquaint us with the problems of poor nations.","options":{"A":"attemptedtoacquaint","B":"attemptsatacquainting","C":"attempttoacquaint","D":"attemptingtoacquaint","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"attemptsatacquainting"},{"question":"It was unanimously resolved that the parties should unitedly undertook launching of popular programmes.","options":{"A":"shouldbeunitedundertook","B":"shouldbeunitedlyundertaken","C":"shouldbeunitedlyundertake","D":"shouldunitedlyundertake","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"shouldunitedlyundertake"},{"question":"They continued to work in the field despite of the heavy rains.","options":{"A":"eventhoughthereisheavyrain","B":"althoughheavilyrains","C":"inspitetheheavyrains","D":"eventhoughitrainedheavily","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"eventhoughitrainedheavily"},{"question":"It is always better to make people realise the importance of discipline than to impose them on it.","options":{"A":"imposeitwiththem","B":"imposethemwithit","C":"imposingthemonit","D":"imposeitonthem","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"imposeitonthem"},{"question":"My doctor knew that I would eventually recover and do kind of work I would be doing before","options":{"A":"wouldhavebeendoing","B":"wouldhavedone","C":"hadbeendone","D":"hadbeendoing","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"hadbeendoing"},{"question":"Later he became unpopular because he tried to lord it on his followers.","options":{"A":"tolorditfor","B":"tolordover","C":"tolorditover","D":"tolorditoveron","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"tolorditover"},{"question":"The crops are dying; it must not had rained.","options":{"A":"musthadnot","B":"mustnotbe","C":"mustnothave","D":"mustnothavebeen","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"mustnothave"},{"question":"The courts are actively to safeguard the interests and the rights of the poor.","options":{"A":"areactivelytosafeguarding","B":"havebeenactivelysafeguarding","C":"havetoactiveinsafeguarding","D":"areactivelyinsafeguarding","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"havebeenactivelysafeguarding"},{"question":"The drama had many scenes which were so humorous that it was hardly possible to keep a straight face.","options":{"A":"hardlypossibleforkeeping","B":"hardlyimpossibleforkeeping","C":"hardlyimpossibleforkeep","D":"hardlypossiblekeeping","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"Hardly does the sun rise when the stars disappeared.","options":{"A":"havethesunrose","B":"hadthesunrisen","C":"didthesunrose","D":"thesunrose","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hadthesunrisen"},{"question":"You will be late if you do not leave now","options":{"A":"didnotleave","B":"left","C":"willnotleave","D":"donothappentoleave","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The train will leave at 8.30 pm, we have been ready by 7.30pm so that, we can reach the station in time.","options":{"A":"were","B":"mustbe","C":"are","D":"shouldhave","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"mustbe"},{"question":"All the allegations levelled against him were found to be baseless.","options":{"A":"levelagainst","B":"levelwith","C":"levellingwith","D":"levelledfor","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"Ramesh is as tall if not,  taller than Mahesh.","options":{"A":"notastallbut","B":"notsotallbutas","C":"astallas,ifnot","D":"asifnot","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"astallas,ifnot"},{"question":"He hesitated to listen to what his brother was saying.","options":{"A":"listenedtohesitate","B":"hesitatedlistento","C":"hesitatestolistening","D":"ishesitatedtolistento","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The prosecution failed in establish in every case today.","options":{"A":"to","B":"on","C":"as","D":"upon","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"to"},{"question":"One of my drawbacks is that I do not have to tolerance of ambiguity.","options":{"A":"donothave","B":"cannothave","C":"amnot","D":"didnothaveto","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"donothave"},{"question":"They should have calmly thought of the advantages that would accrue to them.","options":{"A":"shouldhavebeencalminthinkingabout","B":"shouldbecalmlythoughtof","C":"shallhavetocalmlythoughtof","D":"shouldhavecalmlythinkof","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The easiest of the thing to do is to ask the address to the postman.","options":{"A":"ofthethingstodo","B":"amongthethingsdid","C":"ofthethingtobedone","D":"ofallthethingsdone","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"ofthethingstodo"},{"question":"We demonstrated to them how we were prepared the artistic patterns.","options":{"A":"areprepared","B":"haveprepared","C":"arepreparing","D":"hadprepared","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"hadprepared"},{"question":"Because of his mastery in this field, his suggestions are wide accepted.","options":{"A":"arewidelyaccepted","B":"widelyacceptance","C":"havewidelyaccepted","D":"havebeenwideaccepted","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"arewidelyaccepted"},{"question":"They felt humiliated because they realised that they had cheated.","options":{"A":"havebeencheated","B":"hadbeencheated","C":"hadbeencheating","D":"weretobecheated","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hadbeencheated"},{"question":"Tax evaders should heavily punished as they do it intentionally.","options":{"A":"shouldbeheavyfined","B":"shouldhaveheavilyfined","C":"shallhaveheavyfine","D":"shouldbeheavilyfined","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"shouldbeheavilyfined"},{"question":"We met him immediately after the session in which he had been given a nice speech.","options":{"A":"wouldbegiving","B":"hasbeengiven","C":"willhavegiven","D":"hadgiven","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"hadgiven"},{"question":"For some days the new professor lectured above the heads of his pupils.","options":{"A":"overtheheadof","B":"overtheheadsof","C":"ontheheadsof","D":"throughthehedsof","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"overtheheadsof"},{"question":"The accused now flatly denies have admitted his guilt in his first statement.","options":{"A":"havingadmitted","B":"hadadmitted","C":"havebeenadmitting","D":"hasadmitting","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"havingadmitted"},{"question":"We were still standing in the queue when the film was beginning.","options":{"A":"filmbegan","B":"filmhadbegun","C":"beginningofthefilmwasover","D":"filmbegins","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"filmhadbegun"},{"question":"If I would have realised the nature of job earlier, I would not have accepted it.","options":{"A":"IfIhavehad","B":"IncaseIwouldhave","C":"HadIbeen","D":"HadI","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"IfIhavehad"},{"question":"The crime has growth rapidly in Russia since the disintegration of the communist system.","options":{"A":"rapidcrimehasgrown","B":"crimehasgrownrapidly","C":"crimesgrowrapidly","D":"crimeshavebeenrapidlygrown","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"crimehasgrownrapidly"},{"question":"They failed in their attempt to repair the demolished portion of that building.","options":{"A":"fortheirattempttorepair","B":"intheirattemptingtorepair","C":"withtheirattempttorepair","D":"intheirattemptforrepairs","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"I earnestly believe that you will visit our relatives during your forthcoming trip to Mumbai.","options":{"A":"hadhardlybelievethat","B":"sincerelywouldbelieve","C":"certainlybelievingthat","D":"couldnotbelieve","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"By such time you finish that chapter, I will write a letter.","options":{"A":"Thetimewhen","B":"Bythetime","C":"Bythattime","D":"Thetime","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Bythetime"},{"question":"Though we have kept in mind to try and maintain most facilities, we would like to request you to kindly bear with us any inconvenience that may be caused.","options":{"A":"mustkeepinmindtotryandmaintain","B":"havekeptinmindtryingandmaintain","C":"wouldkeepinmindtotryandtomaintain","D":"shouldhavekeptinmindtotryandtomaintain","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"The tea-estate administration is in such mess there is no leader to set the things right.","options":{"A":"insuchamesshere","B":"inasuchmessthathere","C":"insuchamessthatthere","D":"withsuchamessthatthere","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"insuchamessthatthere"},{"question":"They examined both the samples very carefully but failed to detect any difference in them.","options":{"A":"somedifferencein","B":"somedifferencebetween","C":"anydifferencebetween","D":"anydifferenceamong","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"anydifferencebetween"},{"question":"\"Friends and comrades, the light has gone away from our lives and there is darkness everywhere\"","options":{"A":"off","B":"outof","C":"outfrom","D":"outoff","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"outof"},{"question":"Because of his ill health, the doctor has advised him not to refrain from  smoking.","options":{"A":"tonotrefrainfrom","B":"toresortto","C":"torefrainfrom","D":"toberefrainedfrom","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"torefrainfrom"},{"question":"They have a scheme of rewarding the best of the performers every year.","options":{"A":"abestperformer","B":"thebestamongtheperformer","C":"abestamongperformer","D":"thebestoftheperformer","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"What happens to all those travellers on the ship was not known?","options":{"A":"Whathappenedof","B":"Whathappenedin","C":"Whatisthathappensto","D":"Whathappenedto","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Whathappenedto"},{"question":"Making friends is more rewarding than to make enemies.","options":{"A":"tobeunsociable","B":"tobesociable","C":"beingunsociable","D":"makingenemies","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"makingenemies"},{"question":"The moment they saw me, they were delight","options":{"A":"haddelighted","B":"weredelighted","C":"aredelighted","D":"havebeendelighted","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"weredelighted"},{"question":"He should not had done it.","options":{"A":"hadnot","B":"shouldhadnot","C":"shouldnothave","D":"shouldhave","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"shouldnothave"},{"question":"No sooner do the bells ring than the curtain rose.","options":{"A":"didthebellring","B":"didthebellsring","C":"hadthebellrang","D":"hadthebellrung","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"didthebellsring"},{"question":"The moment the manager came to know fraudulent action of his assistant, he order immediately dismissed him.","options":{"A":"immediatelyorderedhisdismissed","B":"orderedhisimmediatedismissal","C":"immediatelyorderdismissalofhis","D":"orderedforimmediatelydismissalofhim","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"orderedhisimmediatedismissal"},{"question":"The meeting was attended to by all invitees.","options":{"A":"allattendedtoby","B":"attendedbyall","C":"fullyattendedtoby","D":"likeattendingtoall","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"attendedbyall"},{"question":"If he has to spend five hours in the queue, it was really a wastage.","options":{"A":"isareallywastage","B":"isrealawastage","C":"hasreallyawastage","D":"isreallyawastage","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"isreallyawastage"},{"question":"The world has seen small real attempt at population and resource planning.","options":{"A":"few","B":"little","C":"less","D":"afew","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"little"},{"question":"My hair stood off ends when I saw the horrible sight.","options":{"A":"stoodatends","B":"stoodonends","C":"stoodtoends","D":"standsonends","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"stoodonends"},{"question":"The long or short of it is that I do not want to deal with that new firm.","options":{"A":"Thelongandshortofit","B":"Thelongandshortforit","C":"Thelongorshortforit","D":"Theshotandlongforit","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Thelongandshortofit"},{"question":"Can you tell me why did you not speak the truth?","options":{"A":"whydidnotyouspeak","B":"thatwhydidyounotspeak","C":"whyyoudidnotspeak","D":"whydidyounotspoke","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"whyyoudidnotspeak"},{"question":"The people generally try to curry favour with the corrupt but influential person.","options":{"A":"cookfavour","B":"seekfavour","C":"extractfavour","D":"displayfavour","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"I have got some tea, but I do not have a sugar.","options":{"A":"some","B":"got","C":"more","D":"any","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"any"},{"question":"Had I realised how close I was to the edge of the valley, I would not have carried the bags there.","options":{"A":"HadIbeenrealised","B":"IfIwouldhaverealised","C":"WhenIrealised","D":"HadIhadrealised","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"},{"question":"Most of the Indian workers are as healthy as, if not healthier than, British workers.","options":{"A":"asifhealthyasnothealthier","B":"healthierbutnotashealthy","C":"ashealthy,ifnothealthier","D":"sohealthy,ifnothealthier","E":"Nocorrectionrequired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Nocorrectionrequired"}],"sentence-formation":[{"question":"1. I2. immediately3. salary4. my5. want ","options":{"A":"43152","B":"15432","C":"25143","D":"42351","E":"45132"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"15432"},{"question":"1. do2. today3. you4. must5. it ","options":{"A":"34152","B":"25413","C":"12543","D":"51324","E":"45213"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"34152"},{"question":"1. left2. the3. house4. he5. suddenly ","options":{"A":"12435","B":"21354","C":"45123","D":"52341","E":"24135"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"45123"},{"question":"1. medicine2. a3. Neeta4. given5. was ","options":{"A":"51423","B":"25431","C":"15423","D":"42531","E":"35421"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"35421"},{"question":"1. of2. we3. heard4. him5. had ","options":{"A":"42351","B":"52341","C":"25341","D":"25431","E":"25314"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"25314"},{"question":"1. at2. it3. take4. once5. away ","options":{"A":"23514","B":"14352","C":"32514","D":"53214","E":"42315"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"32514"},{"question":"1. him2. the3. to4. charge5. handover ","options":{"A":"42531","B":"51342","C":"41352","D":"45231","E":"52431"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"52431"},{"question":"1. seen2. going3. you4. him5. have ","options":{"A":"35214","B":"35142","C":"32514","D":"35124","E":"53124"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"35142"},{"question":"1. bag?2. you3. seen4. have5. my ","options":{"A":"51432","B":"43512","C":"42351","D":"42153","E":"21435"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"42351"},{"question":"1. killed2. a3. Jaswant4. bear5. wild ","options":{"A":"31254","B":"53124","C":"23145","D":"43125","E":"15234"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"31254"},{"question":"1. was2. and3. Suresh4. kind5. loving ","options":{"A":"31425","B":"54213","C":"34251","D":"15243","E":"12345"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"31425"},{"question":"1. tea2. have3. that4. some5. before ","options":{"A":"43251","B":"24315","C":"24153","D":"52431","E":"41325"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"24153"},{"question":"1. not2. hotel3. comfortable4. was5. the ","options":{"A":"34521","B":"53412","C":"34152","D":"41352","E":"52413"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"52413"},{"question":"1. I2. help3. not4. you5. did ","options":{"A":"24351","B":"15324","C":"45231","D":"43152","E":"52431"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"15324"},{"question":"1. not2. Hari3. away4. run5. did ","options":{"A":"13542","B":"35412","C":"52431","D":"25143","E":"21345"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"25143"}],"sentence-improvement":[{"question":"The workers are hell bent at getting what is due to them.","options":{"A":"hellbentongetting","B":"hellbentforgetting","C":"hellbentupongetting","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"hellbentupongetting"},{"question":"When it was feared that the serfs might go too far and gain their freedom from serfdom, the protestant leaders joined the princes at crushing them.","options":{"A":"intocrushing","B":"incrushing","C":"withoutcrushing","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"incrushing"},{"question":"If the room had been brighter, I would have been able to read for a while before bed time.","options":{"A":"Iftheroomwasbrighter","B":"Iftheroomarebrighter","C":"Hadtheroombeenbrighter","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Hadtheroombeenbrighter"},{"question":"The record for the biggest tiger hunt has not been met since 1911 when Lord Hardinge. then Viceroy of India, shot a tiger than measured 11 feet and 6 inches.","options":{"A":"improved","B":"broken","C":"bettered","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"broken"},{"question":"his powerful desire brought about his downfall.","options":{"A":"Hisintensedesire","B":"Hisdesireforpower","C":"Hisfataldesire","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Hisdesireforpower"},{"question":"Will you kindly open the knot?","options":{"A":"untie","B":"break","C":"loose","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"untie"},{"question":"He sent a word to me that he would be coming late.","options":{"A":"sentword","B":"hadsentaword","C":"sentwords","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"sentword"},{"question":"John had told me that he hasn't done it yet.","options":{"A":"told","B":"tells","C":"wastelling","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"tells"},{"question":"If he had time he will call you.","options":{"A":"wouldhave","B":"wouldhavehad","C":"has","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"has"},{"question":"Will you lend me few rupees in this hour of need?","options":{"A":"lendmeanyrupees","B":"borrowmeafewrupees","C":"lendmeafewrupees","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"lendmeafewrupees"},{"question":"During his long discourse, he did not touch that point.","options":{"A":"touchupon","B":"touchon","C":"touchof","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"touchon"},{"question":"He found a wooden broken chair in the room.","options":{"A":"woodenandbrokenchair","B":"brokenwoodenchair","C":"brokenandwoodenchair","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"brokenwoodenchair"},{"question":"He could not look anything in the dark room.","options":{"A":"lookat","B":"see","C":"seethrough","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"see"},{"question":"The greatest thing in style is to have a use of metaphor.","options":{"A":"knowledge","B":"command","C":"need","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"knowledge"},{"question":"While crossing the highway a five year old child was knocked out by a passing car.","options":{"A":"away","B":"up","C":"down","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"down"},{"question":"hoping not to be disturbed, I sat down in my easy chair to read the book. I won as a prize.","options":{"A":"Ihadwonasaprize","B":"Ihavewonasprize","C":"Ihadtowinasaprize","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Ihadwonasaprize"},{"question":"More than one person was killed in accident.","options":{"A":"werekilled","B":"arekilled","C":"havebeenkilled","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"werekilled"},{"question":"No one could explain how a calm and balanced person like him could penetrate such a mindless act on his friends.","options":{"A":"perpetuate","B":"perpetrate","C":"precipitate","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"perpetrate"},{"question":"Five years ago today, I am sitting in a small Japanese car, driving across Poland towards Berlin.","options":{"A":"wassitting","B":"sat","C":"havebeensitting","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"wassitting"},{"question":"I took the cycle which he bought yesterday.","options":{"A":"thatheboughtyesterday","B":"thatwhichhehadboughtyesterday","C":"thathehadboughtyesterday","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"thathehadboughtyesterday"},{"question":"Please make it a point to send you letter at my address.","options":{"A":"onmyaddress","B":"tomyaddress","C":"inmyaddress","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"tomyaddress"},{"question":"If you are living near a market place you should be ready to bear the disturbances caused by traffic.","options":{"A":"tobearupon","B":"tobearwith","C":"tobearaway","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"tobearwith"},{"question":"I hope you won't object to me watching while you work.","options":{"A":"againstmewatching","B":"metowatch","C":"tomywatching","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"tomywatching"},{"question":"You cannot forbid him leaving.","options":{"A":"heleaving","B":"hisleaving","C":"himtoleave","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"himtoleave"},{"question":"You have come here with a view to insult me.","options":{"A":"toinsultingme","B":"ofinsultingme","C":"forinsultingme","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"toinsultingme"},{"question":"20 kms are not a great distance in these days of fast moving vehicles.","options":{"A":"isnotagreatdistance","B":"isnodistance","C":"aren'tagreatdistance","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"isnotagreatdistance"},{"question":"The more they earn, more they spend.","options":{"A":"Moretheyearn,moretheyspend","B":"Moretheyearn,themoretheyspend","C":"Themoretheyearn,themoretheyspend","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Themoretheyearn,themoretheyspend"},{"question":"It became clear that the strangers were heading into a serious disaster.","options":{"A":"along","B":"towards","C":"for","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"towards"},{"question":"The dissidents hold a great problem in every political party.","options":{"A":"cause","B":"give","C":"pose","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"cause"},{"question":"I would have waited for you at the station if I knew that you would come.","options":{"A":"hadknown","B":"wasknowing","C":"haveknown","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"hadknown"},{"question":"They are social insects, living in communities, regulated by definite laws, each member of society bearing well-defined and separate part in the work of a colony.","options":{"A":"whoarelivingincommunities","B":"livingamongacommunity","C":"wholiveswithacommunity","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"Practically every part of the banana tree is used by man.","options":{"A":"eachpart","B":"anypart","C":"mostpart","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"My opinion for  the film is that it will bag the national ward.","options":{"A":"opinionto","B":"opinionabout","C":"opinionon","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"opinionabout"},{"question":"The end of the examinations is (an) oppurtunity for celebrating.","options":{"A":"chance","B":"moment","C":"occasion","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"moment"},{"question":"We were not the wiser for all this effort to explain the case to us.","options":{"A":"none","B":"neither","C":"nevertheless","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"none"},{"question":"Whenever my students come across new words, I ask them to look for them in the dictionary.","options":{"A":"tolookitup","B":"tolookthemup","C":"tolookatthem","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"tolookthemup"},{"question":"We look forward to hear from you.","options":{"A":"hearing","B":"haveheard","C":"listen","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"hearing"},{"question":"It was indeed a shock for her, but she has later recovered from it.","options":{"A":"since","B":"then","C":"afterwards","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"since"},{"question":"Realising is the significance of technical education for developing country, the government laid aside a large sum on it during the last plan-period.","options":{"A":"laidup","B":"setaside","C":"laidout","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"setaside"},{"question":"If you are not clear about the meaning of a word, it is wise to look to a dictionary.","options":{"A":"lookfor","B":"lookat","C":"lookup","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"lookup"},{"question":"You are warned against committing the same mistake again.","options":{"A":"tocommit","B":"forcommitting","C":"againsttocommit","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"No sooner he had returned home then his mother felt happy.","options":{"A":"hadhereturnedhomewhen","B":"hehadreturnedhomethan","C":"didhereturnhomethan","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"didhereturnhomethan"},{"question":"He should move on to the next point, and not harp one sting only.","options":{"A":"harponstringonly","B":"harponlyonestring","C":"harpupononestringonly","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"harpupononestringonly"},{"question":"Either he or I am going.","options":{"A":"heorIaregoing","B":"heisgoingorIam","C":"Iorheisgoing","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"I hope you vividly remember the premier of the film when I, my wife and you were present in the hall.","options":{"A":"mywife,Iandyou","B":"you,Iandmywife","C":"mywife,youandI","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"mywife,youandI"},{"question":"To get one's name in the Rowland Ward's book of hunting records was the hot ambition of every serious hunter.","options":{"A":"extreme","B":"burning","C":"high","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"high"},{"question":"Taxpayers are to be conscious of their privileges.","options":{"A":"haveto","B":"need","C":"oughtto","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"haveto"},{"question":"As she was suffering from high fever, she could not face the examination.","options":{"A":"bear","B":"suffer","C":"take","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"take"},{"question":"The demonstration passed off peacefully.","options":{"A":"passedout","B":"passedaway","C":"passedon","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"Every time I go in a lift to my sixth floor apartment, I remember the calm and serenity of my ancestral home in the village.","options":{"A":"moveinalift","B":"ascendinalift","C":"takealift","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"takealift"},{"question":"In fact, if it hadn't been for his invaluable advice on so many occasions I wouldn't have achieved anything in life.","options":{"A":"remarkableadvice","B":"valuableadvices","C":"pricelesssuggestion","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"Mr. Smith arrived at India in June last year.","options":{"A":"to","B":"by","C":"in","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"in"},{"question":"But in all these cases conversion from scale have well-formulated.","options":{"A":"canbewell-formulated","B":"arewell-formulated","C":"well-formulated","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"arewell-formulated"},{"question":"With a thundering roar the huge rocket soared up from the launching pad.","options":{"A":"flewup","B":"wentupwards","C":"tookoff","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"tookoff"},{"question":"There is dearth of woman doctor in our state. We shall have to recruit some from the other states.","options":{"A":"womendoctor","B":"womandoctors","C":"womendoctors","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"womendoctors"},{"question":"If you cross the line you will be disqualified.","options":{"A":"crossupontheline","B":"crossontheline","C":"crossouttheline","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"Why the dinosaurs died out is not known.","options":{"A":"itisnotknown","B":"thereasonisnotknown","C":"thatisnotknown","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"His father won't be able to leave for Varnasi until they have arrived.","options":{"A":"untiltheyarrive","B":"untiltheywillhavearrived","C":"untiltheywillarrive","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"untiltheyarrive"},{"question":"I will not go to school, if it shall rain tomorrow.","options":{"A":"itwouldraintomorrow","B":"itwillraintomorrow","C":"itrainstomorrow","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"itrainstomorrow"},{"question":"If I stood alone in defence of truth, and the whole world is banded against me and against truth. I would fight them all.","options":{"A":"willbebanded","B":"werebanded","C":"banded","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"werebanded"},{"question":"He has not and can never be in the good books of his employer because he lacks honesty.","options":{"A":"hasnotandcannotbe","B":"hasnotandcanneverbeen","C":"hasnotbeenandcanneverbe","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"hasnotbeenandcanneverbe"},{"question":"When the examinations were over Anil and me went to our native town.","options":{"A":"meandAnil","B":"AnilandI","C":"IandAnil","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"AnilandI"},{"question":"Our office clock is not so correct as it should be it is usually five minutes fast.","options":{"A":"right","B":"regular","C":"accurate","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"accurate"},{"question":"The cloud of misfortunes appears to have blown out.","options":{"A":"over","B":"up","C":"away","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"over"},{"question":"While we would like that all Indian Children to go to school, we need to ponder why they do not.","options":{"A":"thatalltheIndianchildren","B":"ifallthechildrenofIndia","C":"allIndianchildren","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"allIndianchildren"},{"question":"In India today many of our intellectuals still talk in terms of the French Revolution and the Rights of Man, not appreciating that much has happened since then.","options":{"A":"muchhasbeenhappening","B":"muchhadhappened","C":"muchmighthappen","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"I shall be grateful to you if you are of help to me now.","options":{"A":"help","B":"wouldhelp","C":"helped","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"wouldhelp"},{"question":"The logic of Berlin wall already had been undermined but when the news came through that the wall itself had been opened I jumped into a car.","options":{"A":"hadbeenundeterminedalready","B":"hadalreadybeenundetermined","C":"hadbeenalreadyundetermined","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hadalreadybeenundetermined"},{"question":"Other countries have eradicated this disease ten years ago.","options":{"A":"eradicated","B":"haderadicated","C":"dideradicated","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"eradicated"},{"question":"Young men and women should get habituated to reading and writing about current affairs.","options":{"A":"used","B":"prepared","C":"trained","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"The poor villagers have waited in the bitter cold for more than 4 hours now.","options":{"A":"havebeenwaiting","B":"hadwaited","C":"hasbeenwaiting","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"havebeenwaiting"},{"question":"The old man felled some trees in the garden with hardly no effort at all.","options":{"A":"hardeffort","B":"hardlyanyeffort","C":"ahardlyanyeffort","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hardlyanyeffort"},{"question":"The company goes to great length to ensure that employees can be comfortable in their work environment.","options":{"A":"arecomfortable","B":"willbecomfortable","C":"shouldbecomfortable","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"arecomfortable"},{"question":"I want you to clearly understand that excuses won't do","options":{"A":"youclearlytounderstand","B":"youtounderstandclearly","C":"toclearlyunderstandyou","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"He was fined for careless driving.","options":{"A":"gotfined","B":"fined","C":"wastobefined","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"Although India is still by far a poor country, it can become rich if its natural and human resources are fully utilised.","options":{"A":"fewandfarbetween","B":"byandlarge","C":"byandby","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"byandlarge"},{"question":"The reason why he wrote the letter was because he could not contact him over the phone.","options":{"A":"whyhewrotetheletterwassince","B":"forwhichhewrotetheletterbecause","C":"whyhewrotetheletterwasthat","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"forwhichhewrotetheletterbecause"},{"question":"As he is past his teens now, he can look for himself.","options":{"A":"after","B":"to","C":"around","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"after"},{"question":"There is no more room for you in this compartment.","options":{"A":"thereisnomoreseat","B":"thereisnomorespace","C":"thereisnomoreaccommodation","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"thereisnomorespace"},{"question":"Most donors would seriously protest any effort to extrapolate from such limited data.","options":{"A":"protestagainst","B":"protestat","C":"protestto","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"protestagainst"},{"question":"She says she's already paid me back, but I can't remember, so I 'll have to take her word.","options":{"A":"totakeherwordtrue","B":"totakeheratherword","C":"totakeherwordforit","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"totakeheratherword"},{"question":"If you had attended the meeting, you would have benefited a great deal.","options":{"A":"couldbenefit","B":"wouldbenefit","C":"benefited","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"This matter admits of no excuse.","options":{"A":"admitsto","B":"admitsfrom","C":"admits","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"If he would have tried he would have succeeded.","options":{"A":"istried","B":"wastried","C":"hadtried","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"hadtried"},{"question":"It will be no good trying to find an excuse next time.","options":{"A":"totrytofind","B":"totryfinding","C":"tryingfinding","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"totrytofind"},{"question":"Please remind me of posting these letters to my relatives.","options":{"A":"byposting","B":"topost","C":"forposting","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"topost"},{"question":"Not a word they spoke to the unfortunate wife about it","options":{"A":"didtheyspeak","B":"theywillspeak","C":"theyhadspoken","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"didtheyspeak"},{"question":"Not long back, in Japan, a mysterious nerve gas affected a large number of people.","options":{"A":"effected","B":"infected","C":"infested","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"infected"},{"question":"We had nothing to eat since 8'o clock, this morning.","options":{"A":"havehadnothing","B":"hashadnothing","C":"didhavenothing","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"havehadnothing"},{"question":"We did not see this movie yet.","options":{"A":"haveseen","B":"havenotseen","C":"haveseen","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"havenotseen"},{"question":"My friend was in hospital for a week after an accident.","options":{"A":"through","B":"following","C":"for","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"following"},{"question":"All, but her,  had made an attempt.","options":{"A":"All,butshe,","B":"All,butherself,","C":"All,buther,","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"All,butshe,"},{"question":"Whatever to our other problems. we have no shortcoming to cheap labour in India.","options":{"A":"default","B":"deficit","C":"scarcity","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"scarcity"},{"question":"I have lived in Delhi since I was four.","options":{"A":"amliving","B":"lived","C":"hadlived","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noimprovement"},{"question":"This telephone number is not existing.","options":{"A":"hasnotexisted","B":"doesnotexist","C":"hasnotbeenexisting","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"doesnotexist"},{"question":"I shall not go untill I am invited.","options":{"A":"tillIaminvited","B":"UnlessIaminvited","C":"ifnotIaminvited","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"UnlessIaminvited"},{"question":"He died in the year 1960 at 11pm on 14 July.","options":{"A":"on14Julyintheyear1960at11pm","B":"intheyear1960on14Julyat11pm","C":"at11pmon14Julyintheyear1960","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"at11pmon14Julyintheyear1960"},{"question":"Due to these reason we are all in favour of universal compulsory education.","options":{"A":"Outofthesereasons","B":"Forthesereasons","C":"Bythesereasons","D":"Noimprovement"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Forthesereasons"}],"spellings":[{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Efficient","B":"Treatmeant","C":"Beterment","D":"Employd"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Efficient"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Foreign","B":"Foreine","C":"Fariegn","D":"Forein"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Foreign"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ommineous","B":"Omineous","C":"Ominous","D":"Omenous"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Ominous"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Pessenger","B":"Passenger","C":"Pasanger","D":"Pesanger"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Passenger"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Benefitted","B":"Benifited","C":"Benefited","D":"Benefeted"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Benefited"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Appraise","B":"Commend","C":"Mentanence","D":"Behavior","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Mentanence"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Passion","B":"Fashion","C":"Ration","D":"Tution","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Tution"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Amature","B":"Manual","C":"Nephew","D":"Athletic","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Amature"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Inflamable","B":"Musician","C":"Righteousness","D":"Negotiate","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Inflamable"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Geography","B":"History","C":"Chemistry","D":"Commerce","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theywerequiet","B":"amazedatthe","C":"turnof","D":"events.","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Theywerequiet"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hewasinvited","B":"toattendthe","C":"inauguraloftheallparty","D":"meat","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"meat"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thereligiousleaders","B":"attainedallthe","C":"ceremoniesofother","D":"creeds","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"attainedallthe"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Religiouspeopleare","B":"afraidof","C":"sinful","D":"actions","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Iorderedhimtokeepquite","B":"buthedisobeyed","C":"andcontinued","D":"shouting","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Iorderedhimtokeepquite"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Whennoneoftheadvocates","B":"accepted","C":"hisoffer","D":"heappologisedthem","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"heappologisedthem"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Socialsecurity","B":"andpovertyalleviation","C":"programmesarenotimplimented","D":"withrequiredseriousness","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"programmesarenotimplimented"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Manylegends","B":"superstitionsendowthemoonwithabeautyand","C":"misterywhichwill","D":"lingerforcountlessyears","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"misterywhichwill"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Oneshouldbeablefor","B":"differentiatebetweenwhatis","C":"desirableand","D":"whatisnot","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Oneshouldbeablefor"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thenotorious","B":"bandit","C":"poisonedtheguardandmadea","D":"miraculousescape","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thenon-availability","B":"ofunprocessednatural","C":"resourcesinacountryshouldnotbethe","D":"basicforrejectingthatpossibilityofexportindustry","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"basicforrejectingthatpossibilityofexportindustry"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hisdecisionwasbasedon","B":"adequateand","C":"acurate","D":"information","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"acurate"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hehadexperienced","B":"apurposefully","C":"discussionontopicsofour","D":"interest","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"apurposefully"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Amonstrous","B":"snakecameupthe","C":"hollow","D":"trunkoftree","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Justiceisanenforceable","B":"publicvirtue,strongerin","C":"obligatorythansuchprivatevirtuesasfriendship","D":"charityand","E":"generosity."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"obligatorythansuchprivatevirtuesasfriendship"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"WhenIheard","B":"hisvice","C":"Icouldnotrespond","D":"quickly","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hisvice"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theyappreciated","B":"hiswholehurted","C":"contribution","D":"tothesocialcause","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hiswholehurted"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theattractive","B":"scenepaintedbyhim","C":"fetchedthefirst","D":"price","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"price"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ourcollegeprinciple","B":"neveraccepts","C":"anydonation","D":"frompeoplewithmeagreresources","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Ourcollegeprinciple"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Stereotypes","B":"aredysfunctional","C":"inprojecting","D":"animageofanunbiasedindividual","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Heisamanofamiable","B":"disposition","C":"andemenable","D":"toruleanddiscipline","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"andemenable"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hewasverykin","B":"toprocessallthe","C":"available","D":"information","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Hewasverykin"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Peopleinourcountryaredistressed","B":"bythespateofstrikes,analmost","C":"perpetualgoslowand","D":"increadibilylowproductivity","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"increadibilylowproductivity"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hewaspolite","B":"butferminhis","C":"dealingswiththe","D":"foreigners","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"butferminhis"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thefuneral","B":"wasplainandostentatious","C":"Itdiffered","D":"innothingfromtheordinery","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"innothingfromtheordinery"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thefacesofthe","B":"twinswereso","C":"identicalthatwecouldnot","D":"differentiatebetweenthem","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"identicalthatwecouldnot"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"scentshave","B":"utter","C":"disregardforwealthandworldlymatters","D":"trunkoftree","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"scentshave"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thephilosophers","B":"believethatbymakingmensee","C":"reasonthroughargument,societywouldbechangedandhumanbehaviour","D":"improvd","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"improvd"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"stationary","B":"itemsgointoaninventory","C":"assiduously","D":"prepared","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"stationary"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theycannotbuy","B":"certain","C":"medicineswhichareextremely","D":"expensive","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allcorrect"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thefaster","B":"headjusttoanovelsituation","C":"thesoon","D":"willheberewarded","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"thesoon"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Tosolvea","B":"problem,oneneedstohave","C":"intelligentandfirm","D":"determination","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"intelligentandfirm"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Peopletakeundue","B":"advantageofhis","C":"simplicityand","D":"chithim","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"chithim"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theconclusion","B":"wasincorrectbecauseitwas","C":"drownedonincomplete","D":"date","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"drownedonincomplete"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theyexcepted","B":"oursuggestionand","C":"transformeditinto","D":"practice","E":"Allcorrect"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Theyexcepted"}],"spotting-errors":[{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Wediscussedabouttheproblemsothoroughly","B":"ontheeveoftheexamination","C":"thatIfounditveryeasytoworkitout.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Wediscussedabouttheproblemsothoroughly"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"AnIndianship","B":"ladenwithmerchandise","C":"gotdrownedinthePacificOcean.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"gotdrownedinthePacificOcean."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Icouldnotputupinahotel","B":"becausetheboardingandlodgingcharges","C":"wereexorbitant.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Icouldnotputupinahotel"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"TheIndianradio","B":"whichwaspreviouslycontrolledbytheBritishrulers","C":"isfreenowfromthenarrowvestedinterests.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"isfreenowfromthenarrowvestedinterests."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"IfIhadknown","B":"thisyesterday","C":"Iwillhavehelpedhim.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Iwillhavehelpedhim."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Alotoftraveldelayiscaused","B":"duetotheinefficiencyandlackofgoodmanagement","C":"onbehalfoftherailways.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"onbehalfoftherailways."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Oneofthemembers","B":"expresseddoubtif","C":"theMinisterwasanatheist.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"expresseddoubtif"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ihavegot","B":"myM.Sc.degree","C":"in1988.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Ihavegot"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Havingreceivedyourletter","B":"thismorning,wearewriting","C":"tothankyouforthesame.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noerror."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ifyoulendhimabook","B":"hewilllendittosomeoneelse","C":"andneveryouwillgetitback.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"andneveryouwillgetitback."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"AccordingtotheBible","B":"itismeekandhumble","C":"whoshallinherittheearth.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"itismeekandhumble"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Dotherosesinyourgardensmell","B":"moresweetly","C":"thanthoseinours?","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"moresweetly"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"BlockofResidentialflats","B":"arecomingup","C":"nearourhouse.","D":"Noerror"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"BlockofResidentialflats"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Youcanget","B":"alltheinformationthatyouwant","C":"inthisbook.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"alltheinformationthatyouwant"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Thestudentswere","B":"awaitingfor","C":"thearrivalofthechiefguest.","D":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"awaitingfor"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Severalissuesraising","B":"inthemeetingcould","C":"beamicablyresolved","D":"duetohistactfulhandling.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Severalissuesraising"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hedesertedthepathofhonour","B":"inorderto","C":"satisfyhisambition","D":"andthenwentdownhisdoomveryquickly.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"andthenwentdownhisdoomveryquickly."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Nitin'snephew,wholives","B":"inBangalore,iseagertotravelto","C":"Delhitohave","D":"aglimpseofthecapital.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noerror."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Bible","B":"canbe","C":"regardedas","D":"agreat.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Bible"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theinstitute","B":"impartstraining","C":"in","D":"theFrench.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"theFrench."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hisfatherpromisedto","B":"givehimanythingwhathe","C":"wantsifhe","D":"passesintheexamination.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"givehimanythingwhathe"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Beingaveryfastworker,","B":"heisalwaysliking","C":"byallhiscolleagues.","D":"andsuperiorstoo.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"heisalwaysliking"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Whileluminariesofthedanceworld","B":"haveadearthofopportunitiestodisplaytheirart","C":"upcomingdancerssufferfrom","D":"anunfortunatelackofexposure.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"haveadearthofopportunitiestodisplaytheirart"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ishallbeable","B":"tocompletetheworkin","C":"stipulatedtimeprovide","D":"youdonotdisturbme.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"stipulatedtimeprovide"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Ourneighbourshadrepeated","B":"thesameillogicalsequenceofactivities","C":"ifwehadnotbroughtthe","D":"factstotheirnotice.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Ourneighbourshadrepeated"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Wearehappy","B":"toknowthat","C":"theprojectcompleted","D":"strictlyaspertheschedule.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"theprojectcompleted"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hewastoo","B":"irritatedto","C":"concentrateonhiswork","D":"foralongtime.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noerror."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Theenvironmentinwhich","B":"companiesoperating","C":"todayis","D":"undergoingFreneticchanges.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"companiesoperating"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Hehasbeenundergoing","B":"thespecialtrainingcourse","C":"whicheachoftheemployees","D":"isrequiredto.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"isrequiredto."},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Alotofmoney","B":"iswastedin","C":"theduplicationofwork","D":"inanyorganisation.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"iswastedin"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"Wedecidednottellto","B":"thepatientabout","C":"thediseasehewas","D":"sufferingfrom.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Wedecidednottellto"},{"question":"(solve as per the direction given above)","options":{"A":"WhenI","B":"lastseehim","C":"hewas","D":"inCalcutta.","E":"Noerror."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"lastseehim"}],"synonyms":[{"question":"CORPULENT","options":{"A":"Lean","B":"Gaunt","C":"Emaciated","D":"Obese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Obese"},{"question":"BRIEF","options":{"A":"Limited","B":"Small","C":"Little","D":"Short"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Short"},{"question":"EMBEZZLE","options":{"A":"Misappropriate","B":"Balance","C":"Remunerate","D":"Clear"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Misappropriate"},{"question":"VENT","options":{"A":"Opening","B":"Stodge","C":"End","D":"Pasttenseofgo"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Opening"},{"question":"AUGUST","options":{"A":"Common","B":"Ridiculous","C":"Dignified","D":"Petty"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Dignified"},{"question":"CANNY","options":{"A":"Obstinate","B":"Handsome","C":"Clever","D":"Stout"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Clever"},{"question":"ALERT","options":{"A":"Energetic","B":"Observant","C":"Intelligent","D":"Watchful"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Watchful"},{"question":"It is very difficult to retain all that you hear in the class.","options":{"A":"keep","B":"recall","C":"preserve","D":"conserve"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"keep"},{"question":"The great artist life was full of vicissitudes.","options":{"A":"sorrows","B":"misfortunes","C":"changes","D":"surprises"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"changes"},{"question":"She has an insatiable love for music.","options":{"A":"unsatisfiable","B":"unchanging","C":"irreconcilable","D":"undesirable"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"unsatisfiable"},{"question":"The great dancer impressed the appreciative crowd by his nimble movements.","options":{"A":"Unrhythmic","B":"lively","C":"quickening","D":"clear"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"quickening"},{"question":"The visitor had a bohemian look.","options":{"A":"hostile","B":"unconventional","C":"sinister","D":"unfriendly"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"unconventional"},{"question":"The bullet wound proved to be fatal and the soldier died immediately.","options":{"A":"grievous","B":"dangerous","C":"serious","D":"deadly"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"deadly"},{"question":"The attitude of Western countries towards the Third World Countries is rather callous to say the least.","options":{"A":"passive","B":"unkind","C":"cursed","D":"unfeeling"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"unfeeling"}],"verbal-analogies":[{"question":"DIVA:OPERA","options":{"A":"producer:theatre","B":"director:drama","C":"conductor:bus","D":"thespian:play"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"thespian:play"},{"question":"GRAIN:SALT","options":{"A":"shard:pottery","B":"shred:wood","C":"blades:grass","D":"chip:glass"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"chip:glass"},{"question":"THRUST:SPEAR","options":{"A":"mangle:iron","B":"scabbard:sword","C":"bow:arrow","D":"fence:epee"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"fence:epee"},{"question":"PAIN:SEDATIVE","options":{"A":"comfort:stimulant","B":"grief:consolation","C":"trance:narcotic","D":"ache:extraction"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"grief:consolation"},{"question":"LIGHT:BLIND","options":{"A":"speech:dumb","B":"language:deaf","C":"tongue:sound","D":"voice:vibration"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"speech:dumb"}]}